<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The heart of N-England rent at the blasphemies of the present generation. Or A brief tractate, concerning the doctrine of the Quakers, demonstrating the destructive nature thereof, to religion, the churches, and the state, with consideration of the remedy against it. : Occasional satisfaction to objections, and confirmation of the contrary trueth. / By John Norton ...</title>
            <author>Norton, John, 1606-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W12678</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097875</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2574:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The heart of N-England rent at the blasphemies of the present generation. Or A brief tractate, concerning the doctrine of the Quakers, demonstrating the destructive nature thereof, to religion, the churches, and the state, with consideration of the remedy against it. : Occasional satisfaction to objections, and confirmation of the contrary trueth. / By John Norton ...</title>
                  <author>Norton, John, 1606-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green, at Cambridg in New-England.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  New England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Heart of N-England</hi> rent at the BLASPHEMIES OF THE PRESENT <hi>GENERATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or A brief Tractate concerning the Doctrine of the Quakers, Demonſtrating the deſtructive nature thereof, to Religion, the Churches, and the State, with conſideration of the Remedy againſt it.</p>
            <p>Occaſional Satisfaction to Objections, and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the contrary Trueth.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN NORTON,</hi> Teacher of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Boſton.</hi> Who was appointed thereunto by the Order of the <hi>GENERAL COURT.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I know thy works, and thy labour, and patience, and how thou canst not bear them which are evill; and thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them lyars <bibl>Rev: 2.2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Samuel Green,</hi> at CAMBRIDG in <hi>New-England.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:171454:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171454:2"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP: 1.</hi>
The Original of the Doctrine of the Quakers. With ſome of their principal Heterodoxies. A brief Demonſtration of three distinct Perſons, in the Divine Eſſence. Satisfaction to ſome Objections. And a Vindication of ſome Scriptures.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen that grand-Heretick <hi>Swenok feild,</hi> who in eighteen yeares had publiſhed fifty ſcripts, (ſuch as they were) ſometime troubled <hi>Luther.</hi> with his papers, which he ſent unto him for an anſwer: his returne was quick, ſaying to the meſſenger, the Deuil was the author of them: the Lord rebuke thee O Satan! <hi>Quod-vult-deus</hi> whileſt he deſired <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> to publiſh a tract of al the hereſies which infeſted the church in thoſe dayes, diſcerned the undertaking to be too immenſe &amp; great: this <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo perceiving being about to write againſt the Libertines, preſently determined (omitting the reſt of their wild &amp; endleſſe heterodoxies) to addreſſe himſelfe unto the enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; refutation, of ſome of their principall, &amp; portentous tenets. <hi>Luthers</hi> anſwer may ſeeme too ſhort: <hi>Auguſtines</hi> taſke is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged too long, <hi>Calvins</hi> example in this brief treatiſe I ſhall in part (God aſſiſting) endeavour to follow.</p>
               <p>The recalling of the begin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing of the <hi>Father of lyes,</hi> may ſoon lead us to the Original of Errour: but the full diſcovery of its progreſſe &amp; encreaſe, is not to be expected, untill that day, <hi>which ſhall bring to light,—all the workes of darkneſs.</hi> He that deſires no: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderably to informe himſelfe,<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>naeus de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſibus ante Chriſtú.</note> concerning the attempts of the old Serpent, upon this deſigne, from the begin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing of time, untill the times of Chriſt, may conſult antiquity not unprofitably, for that end. In the very Apoſtles times wee read of <hi>Deceivers,</hi> who pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to higher attainments, to be <hi>ſtars of light,</hi> &amp; that of the firſt magnitude,<note place="margin">Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e 13.</note> but were indeed <hi>Raging waves of the ſea fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng out their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171454:3"/>
owne ſhame, wandring ſtars, to whom is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the doctrine of the <hi>Enthuſiaſts in Germany,</hi> &amp; <hi>Libertines,</hi> in the low-countryes, was a dead ſea of heterodoxy, conſiſting in a great degree of the pernicious waters of old hereſyes, till then out of mind for many hundred yeares, and that the doctrine of the Quakers (as to the ſubſtance of it) is but the opening of that vaſt and horrid ſinke: (ſuch as makes the land to ſtink in the noſtrils both of God and man, more then the Frogs that ſometime annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Egypt) But the ſame doctrine of the <hi>Enthuſiasts</hi> &amp; <hi>Libertines,</hi> of the laſt Century, though in a ſecond edition, is thus manifeſted.</p>
               <p>The great doctrine of
<list>
                     <item>The Trinitie.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>The Scripture.</item>
                     <item>Goſpel
<list>
                           <item>Ordinances.</item>
                           <item>Miniſtry.</item>
                           <item>Order.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Chriſtian Magiſtrate, &amp; Civil Order.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Are the Objects, that the three following ſtages of heterodoxie, finally engaged &amp; engage againſt, and that ſo, as the ſecond <hi>viz: Enthuſiasts,</hi> &amp; <hi>Libertines,</hi> were indeed not only actors &amp; Preachers of what was prepared, but alſo in ſome conſiderable degree, Collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors out of the ſcatterings of their Predeceſsors, to compleat their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of falſe doctrine: but the laſt, viz: the Quakers, are more deluded by their maſters in wickedneſs: whither Satan, or any Jeſuitical, or other malignant &amp; ſerpentine agents, who making uſe of the <hi>myſtery of iniquity,</hi> thus farr perfected to their hand, notably abuſe their ignorant, and ſelfe conceited proſelytes: whileſt under the pretence of new light, they communicate both ſtale and exploded hereſies &amp; error, to be diſſeminated by them the ſecond time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Certain old heterodoxies, concerning the forementioned heads</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or the like the <hi>Enthuſiaſts, &amp; Libertines</hi> might ariſe</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praxeas,</hi> who lived in the year two hundred, taught that there was but one perſon, only in divers reſpects, called the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt. After ariſeth <hi>Sabellius</hi> under <hi>Valerian,</hi> affirming that in the Divine Eſſence, there were three names, but denyed that there were three diſtinct ſubſiſtences, or perſons.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Christ:</hi> the enmity of the <hi>father of lyes</hi> hath no where more ſhown it ſelfe then in his malignant contrivances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171454:3"/>
the perſon &amp; office of <hi>Christ. The Gnoſticks denyed Ieſus</hi> to be the <hi>Christ: Cerinibus</hi> denyeth the Dvinity, <hi>Neſtorius</hi> affirmeth two perſons. <hi>Eutiches</hi> denyeth the two Natures <hi>Marcion</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his paſſion to be imaginary, not reall. <hi>Ignatius</hi> mentions incredulous men, who were aſhamed of the trueth of the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. ſome pretended themſelves to be <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the ſcriptures, conſidered as the rule of life. the <hi>Meſſalian Enthuſiaſts</hi> expected divine raptures without the word, they waited for the operation of a certain Daemon, or a ſpirit: and this operation (which indeed was the operation of the Devil) they eſteemed to be the preſence of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp; called their fantaſies prophecyes. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in one of his ſermons concerning hereſies, writes againſt ſuch, who in thoſe times held that the words of the ſcripture were to be taken ſimply, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration had unto what they ſignifyed.</p>
               <p>Concerning Goſpel Ordinances, Miniſtry, &amp; Order: the <hi>authors</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews, Jude, and Iohn,</hi> make mention of Apoſtates there from ſuch who in their dayes forſook the church aſſemblies, ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues, &amp; went out from the fellowſhip of the Saints. Heb. 10.25. Iude. 19.1. Iohn. 2.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jude</hi> alſo informeth us of ſuch who deſpiſed Dominion, ſpake evill of dignitie, and periſhed in the gainſaying of <hi>Core:</hi> which conſiſted in murmuring, &amp; rebelling againſt <hi>Moſes and Aaron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Gnoſticks</hi> repreſented themſelves perfect, againſt whom, <hi>John</hi> is conceived to write. 1. Epiſtle 1.8. The old <hi>Catharoi</hi> called <hi>puritans</hi> affirmed alſo that they were perfect, &amp; without ſin.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The tenets of the Enthuſiaſts, &amp; Libertines, concerning the ſame heads of Religion. The Enthuſiaſts began about <hi>1521.</hi> The Libertines in Calvin's time, both Sects vexed the Church and State many yeares.</head>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Trinitie,</hi> they acknowledged three:<note place="margin">Sleidan com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> lib. 5 et 10.</note> but they denyed the Father, Son, &amp; Holy-Ghoſt to be three diſtinct Perſons.</p>
                  <p>Concerning Chriſt: they ſaid Chriſt incarnate was nothing but a godly man, or a believer made of a body, and an opinion.<note place="margin">Lu. Ofiand. Cent. 16. lib. 2. cap. 33</note> they made euery ſaint equal with God, according to the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Libertines</hi> each one of them was Chriſt.<note place="margin">Calvin ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinos. Guy de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> hence <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> as offended with thoſe who aſked him how he did, was wont to anſwer: how do I? can Chriſt do amiſs?</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Scripture conſidered as the Rule of life: <hi>Swenck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171454:4"/>
ſaith they make an idol of the word.<note place="margin">Mr Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Surv: when the Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thors by him Cited in the Marge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ch. p. 3.</note> who eſteem it as <hi>the Power of God through faith unto ſalvation: i. e.</hi> who eſteem it as the meanes whereby the ſpirit worketh grace in the heart of the hearer. he goeth through <hi>Sweden, Normberg, Vlms, Tubingia,</hi> in private houſes accuſing the paſtors, that no man was the better for their preaching: extolling the ſpirit that doth all, underſtand without the word; as the meanes <hi>The Libertines,</hi> denyed all preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>Officers, Sacraments, Church-aſſemblies, ſinging of Pſalmes.</hi> they accounted the ſcripture as a dead letter, &amp; neglected it, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to follow the ſpirit: yet, they uſed it in ſpeaking and writing becauſe (through the peoples good opinion thereof) they found it a fit meanes, to inſinuate themſelves, with their diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall opinions, into their heart. they rejected the ſcripture and pretended the ſpirit for their rule.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Magiſtrates; Muncer</hi> defameth, &amp; detracts from the <hi>miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> afterwards falls with like violonce upon the Magiſtrate, hoping by making void theſe two orders, they ſhould prevaile upon the flock. he teacheth parity, reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of dignities. Thoſe in <hi>Germany</hi> held that none with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience could exerciſe the power of a magiſtrate, that is, none but ſuch who were of their mind: witneſs both their doctrine, &amp; practice, in <hi>Munſter</hi> and elſe where, they held alſo <hi>that it was lawfull for the people to depoſe their Magiſtrates being unbelievers,</hi> and they counted all unbelievers who were not of their mind.</p>
                  <p>They pretended an immediate miſſion, &amp; to act from the ſpirit, and by vertue of an immediate command, above the triall of the ſcripture. <hi>Muncer</hi> ſaid that by his divine revelations, he muſt Judge of the Bible.</p>
                  <p>They carryed it in the beginning very faire before all men, for they had alwayes in their mouths the faith and fear of God, the mortification of the fleſh, &amp; mention of the croſs. They affected a grave countenance &amp; poſture, wore plain apparell, uſed few words, <hi>cryed in the ſtreets repent, repent.</hi> they were reſerved as to the diſcouery of their myſteryes, untill they were hopefully aſſured of their follower, they ſtudyes to ſpeak equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocally, ſo as their words might carry divers ſences. they lifted up themſelves above others, &amp; gloryed to be called <hi>spirituales,</hi> men of the ſpirit. The fourth order of the <hi>Libertines</hi> (for they had many orders) was of the holy and ſinleſſe ones.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171454:4"/>
                  <head>The tenets of the Quakers concerning the ſame heads of Religion.</head>
                  <p>Concerning the Trinity; they acknowledg that there is one God and three, viz; the Father, Son, and Holy-Ghoſt; <hi>but they deny that theſe three, are diſtinct Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning Chriſt: <hi>they deny Christ to be God &amp; man in one Perſon, they deny Chriſt to be a diſtinct Perſon from the Perſon of the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The tenents here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, appear from publiſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed papers, with the names of the Authors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, or by word of mouth.</note> 
                     <hi>they deny Christ to be a diſtinct Perſon from any of his members,</hi> they acknowledge ſuch a Chriſt as unchriſts Chriſt, when they ſay Chriſt manifeſt in the fleſh, they meane not according to the ſenſe of the ſcripture, but fallaciouſly.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Scripture, conſidered as the Rule of life: <hi>They deny the ſcripture or written word to be the Rule of life, &amp; make the light within them, &amp; the ſpirit without the ſcripture, to be their guide,</hi> They account Church-inſtituted-worſhip, &amp; waiting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God for the efficacious preſence and co-operation of the Spirit of grace in the miniſtery of the word and Sacraments for converſion &amp; edification to be idolatry. And the political Order of Church-Officers and members, they affirme to be an Image.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Magiſtrate: they own none as lawfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, who are not of their way.</hi> Their non-acknowledgement of the Magiſtrate as now eſtabliſhed in all chriſtian ſtates, is more then manifeſt.</p>
                  <p>They pretend unto an Immediate call, &amp; to act from the ſpirit <hi>and an infallible light within them above the triall of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they will not acknowledge that they ſin, but profeſs perfection of degrees in this life,</hi> and publiſh ſmart &amp; ſarcaſticall invectives againſt miniſters who teach the Contrary.</p>
                  <p>How farre the deportment of the Quakers, anſwereth to the outward guiſe and geſt of the ſectaryes in Germany, &amp; the low-countreyes prementioned, he that ſeeth the one; &amp; heareth of the other, may eaſily Judge. The premiſes ſhow the Quak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to be rather imitators of the <hi>Enthuſiaſts &amp; Libertines,</hi> then Innovators.</p>
                  <p>That the perſons thus opinionated are called Quakers; is not from their tenets, but from the geſture where with they are acted, at or about the time of the reception of their revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or, when elſe, in reference to credit their doctrines. This very geſture as circumſtanced, renders their way in no ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree ſuſpitious: it being the ancient and known manner of Satan,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171454:5"/>
when he inſpired his <hi>Enthuſiasts,</hi> to afflict the bodyes of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments with paines &amp; thoſe often in their bowells, and to agitate them with <hi>Antick and uncouth motions,</hi> &amp; in particular with this of <hi>quaking &amp; trembling:</hi> thereby to amuſe ignorant ſpectators with a ſuperſtitious aſtoniſhment, and ſo to diſpoſe them to the expectation of ſome ſtrange diſcovery preter-humane in pretence <hi>divine</hi> but indeed <hi>diabolicall. Seneca</hi> preſenteth the <hi>Sybil i. e.</hi> Satans propheteſs at the act of receiving her <hi>Oracles,</hi> from the revelation of the Devil; <hi>pale-faced with eyes wrung, in an unwonted and fearfull manner,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca in Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mem.</note> 
                     <hi>as alſo quaking &amp; trembling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Silet repente Phoebus, &amp; pallor genas</l>
                     <l>Creber<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> totum poſſidet Corpus tremor.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Horat. lib. 1. Ode. 16. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> adytis quatit &amp;c:</note>At <hi>Pythia</hi> a place in <hi>Phocis, Apollo</hi> that is the Devil, is reported by the Poet, to cauſe his Prieſt to quake. <hi>Gregory of Nice</hi> ſpeaking of this ſubiect, beſide the hair hanging down about their eares looſe, &amp; eyes averſe, maketh mention of foaming at the mouth and much like hereunto is what we read in <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man inſpired (underſtand by Satan) panting and having her head <hi>Contort</hi> that is wryed in ſo ſtrange a manner, as was affrighting to behold. Many inſtances of this nature, might be produced, but I ſhall only further mind the Reader of the cuſtome of the <hi>Powa's</hi> or Indian <hi>Wizards,</hi> in this wilderneſs; whoſe bodies at the time of their <hi>diabolicall</hi> practiſes, are at this day vexed and agitated in a ſtrange unwonted &amp; dreadfull manner. This verifieth that old proverb, that Satan is Gods ape. yet the examples of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> going <hi>naked &amp; barefoot, i. e.</hi> in a bare habit like a poore ſlave or bond man that is carryed into captivity <hi>Chap:</hi> 20.2. Of <hi>Ezekiel, ſmiting his hand, and ſtamping with his foot.</hi> Ezek. 6.11. Of <hi>Daniel's great quaking,</hi> which fell upon him at the ſight of that <hi>viſion</hi> Dan: 10.7. with the like, do not juſtifie this geſture. Their cauſes were divine, circumſtanced to edification, and extraordinary not cuſtomary to the <hi>Prophets</hi> themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Concerning three diſtinct Perſons in the divine Eſſence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who being the brightneſs of his glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon.</hi> Heb: 1.3. The firſt manner of exiſtence in the Divine Being, is here called <hi>Hypoſtaſis,</hi> which imports a diſtinct ſubſiſtence.</p>
                  <p>If the Father <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Correlate</hi> be a diſtinct ſubſiſtence, there is the ſame reaſon of the Son, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z</hi> the <hi>Relate.</hi> If the Father be a diſtinct ſubſiſtence, the Son is a diſtinct ſubſiſtence. If the Son be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171454:5"/>
a diſtinct ſubſiſtence, the Father is a diſtinct ſubſiſtence, the Son is as diſtinct from the Father,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de trinit. lib. 7 c. 4.</note> as the Father is from the Son, that which the Greek calls <hi>hypoſtaſis,</hi> the latine calleth <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona,</hi> from which laſt is our Engliſh word perſon.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſpeaking of the Father Iohn. 5.32. calleth him <hi>another: there is another that beareth witneſs of mee.</hi> likewiſe ſpeaking of the Holy-Ghoſt he calleth him <hi>another</hi> Iohn. 14.16. <hi>I will pray the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; he ſhall give you another Comforter.</hi> this predicate <hi>another</hi> is unintelligible of the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> for ſo the Father Son &amp; Holy-Ghoſt are one. Iohn. 10.30. 1 Iohn. 5.7; therfore it muſt proceed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Subſiſtence;</hi> what is more manifeſt then that another <hi>Subſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and another ſubſiſtence, ſpeake diſtinct ſubſiſtences.</p>
                  <p>The diſtinction of the <hi>perſons, or Subſiſtences,</hi> is manifeſt from the relative properties of <hi>begetting,</hi> being <hi>begotten, and proceeding,</hi> Pſal. 2.7. Iohn. 15.27. <hi>Begetting,</hi> is diſtinct from being <hi>begotten,</hi> being <hi>begotten</hi> from <hi>begetting,</hi> both from <hi>proceeding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A perſonal act is God neceſſarily, relatively and in an Incommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable manner, acting within or upon himſelfe. Now theſe acts of the Perſons one upon another argue the <hi>diſtinctnes</hi> of the ſubſiſtences, viz: <hi>to beget, being begotten, &amp; proceeding,</hi> God in the firſt man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence is conſidered as acting upon himſelfe in a way of <hi>underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> in the ſecond manner of Subſiſtence as reflecting upon himſelf <hi>underſtood;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. de trinit. lib. 5. c. 11 &amp; lib. 6. c. 5.</note> in the third manner of ſubſiſtence as <hi>willing of &amp; delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in himſelfe.</hi> Hence the Spirit is called the hand of the Trinity, proceeding from the two other perſons, as the <hi>Love</hi> of them both: which ſelfe-ſufficient, and infinitely bleſſed Communion of God, in and with himſelf, before there was either mountain or hill, while as yet he had not made the earth: wee read of Prov. 8.30. <hi>Then was I by him, as one brought up with him &amp; I was dayly his delight, rejoycing alwayes before him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The diſtinction of the Perſons further appeares, from the <hi>order,</hi> of their operations upon the creature; held forth in their miſſion, or ſending, the ſecond Perſon is ſent from the Father Iohn. 8.42. <hi>Ieſus ſaid unto them, if God were your father, yee would love mee, for I proceeded forth &amp; came from God: neither came I of my ſelfe, but he ſent mee.</hi> The Holy-Ghoſt is ſent from the Father &amp; the Son: <hi>whom the Father will ſend John.</hi> 14 26. <hi>whom I will ſend John.</hi> 15.26. Sending imports two things, Firſt an eternall relative property of the Divine Eſſence, the order &amp; original whereof is not of it ſelf.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171454:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Secondly, a deſignation of the Perſon diſtinguiſhed by this relative property unto ſome work concerning the creature to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in time. Now evident it is that he which ſendeth and he which is ſent are diſtinct. That the Father ſending &amp; the Son ſent by the Father: the Father and Son ſending the Spirit, and the Spirit ſent by the Father &amp; Son are diſtinct ſubſiſtences and not the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Concerning ſatisfaction to ſome Objections.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object: </seg>1</label> The Church was without the Scripture, or written Word, for the ſpace of 2454 yeares, untill <hi>Moſes:</hi> during which ſpace, the Doctrine of Life was communicated <hi>VOCALLY;</hi> by the <hi>Patriarches:</hi> Therefore there is no need of the Scripture, or written Word.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> There are many Reaſons obvious, why the Tradition of the Rule of life by word of mouth, might better ſuit the ſtate of the Church, in the time of the long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>evity of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> then now: as alſo, why God ſaw not good, to continue unto after ages, ſuch and ſo frequent extraordinary manifeſtations of himſelf, as wee read of in thoſe elder times. Why God diſpenſed the Rule of life then by word of mouth, &amp; not by writing: a principal reaſon thereof was his good pleaſure: The ſame good pleaſure may ſtand for a principal reaſon, way he diſpenſeth the Rule of life now by the word written, and not by vocall tradition. <hi>Even ſo Father, becauſe it pleaſeth thee.</hi> Diſtinguiſh between neceſſity abſolute, &amp; neceſſity according to Divine conſtitution. God according to his abſolute power, can communicate the rule of life by what means he pleaſeth: therefore the ſcripture is not neceſſary abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But Gods will being to communicate the Rule of life by his written word hence the ſcripture is neceſsary by neceſsity of divine conſtitution, or appointment. Whileſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs God give them <hi>Manna,</hi> bread from heaven in an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary manner: After their comming into <hi>Canaan,</hi> he changeth his diſpenſation, and giveth them bread in the ordinary way of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>griculture or tillage. He could ſtill have ſupplyed them in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary way, out he would not. The <hi>Maana</hi> ceaſed. Joſh. 5.12</p>
                  <p>Not the letter without the mind of the Author, nor the Spirit without the letter, but the Scripture, <hi>i. e.</hi> the word-written as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the ſenſe of the author is the Rule of life. Diſtinguiſh between <hi>Moral-obliging-power,</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthning-Phyſical-power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171454:6"/>All the <hi>ſtrengthning-Phyſical-power,</hi> whereby we are enabled to obey the Rule, is from the Spirit, but the <hi>Moral-obliging-power</hi> is from the Scripture it ſelf or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand as denoting the will of God ſignifyed thereby. Surely they are under a Rule, who have not the Spirit. Since the Canon of the Scripture is cloſed, ſo farr is the Spirit from being a Rule of life that to us it is not the Spirit, but as it moves agreeably to the written word: Hereby we are taught to diſcerne between the Spirit of trueth and the Spirit of error.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> The words of the Scripture are to be taken ſimply, without interpretation or conſideration, of what is ſignifyed by them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> This Objection expoſeth Scripture to the imputation of <hi>non-ſence:</hi> which cannot be without at leaſt the reflexion of blaſphemy interpretative, upon the author. It was wont to be ſaid <hi>Scripture lyeth not in the Sound, but in the Sence.</hi> They are not the inkie cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters; without the mind of the author, that can conſtitute Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But taking the mind of the objection more favourably, as proceeding only againſt any other ſenſe, or interpretation to be given of Scripture, then according to the ſound of the words in a proper or (according to ſome) in a literall ſence. yet it unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a conſiderable part of the Scripture unto us, &amp; becommeth a fruithfull womb of confuſion, error, and abſurdity, ſhould it ſtand in force. The example, thoſe words [<hi>that they may be one as wee are one. John.</hi> 17.22.] give an uncertain ſound. Nay the Papiſts <hi>Tranſſubſtantiation, &amp; Origen's, caſtration</hi> are hence warrantable. Diſtinguiſh between <hi>no interpretation, miſ-interpretation, &amp; ſound interpretation. Non-ſenſe, a falſe ſenſe, and the true ſenſe.</hi> The two former are wiles of the enemy, the laſt is the gift of the Spirit of trueth, and a great part of the work of the Miniſtry. <hi>So they read in the book of the Law of God, distinctly: and gave the ſenſe, &amp; cauſed them to underſtand the reading.</hi> Nehem. 8.8. He expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them in all the Scriptures, the things concerning himſelf Luke 24.27. <hi>Philip ſaid, underſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt; and he ſaid, how can I, except ſome man ſhould guide me!</hi> Act. 8.30, 31</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> 
                     <hi>Nothing is to be acknowledged Scripture-trueth, but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein in expreſs termes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>A Scripture conſequence; is a Trueth evidently &amp; neceſſarily ariſing out of a propoſition, held forth therein in expreſs termes;</hi> So that: if the doctrine conteined in the propoſition held forth in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs termes be true, then is the doctrine conteined therein by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171454:7"/>
conſequence, alſo true. Thoſe trueths are Scripture-trueths, which are conteined or held forth in the Scriptures: though not in expreſs termes, yet by juſt &amp; evident conſequence. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6 <hi>I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Iſaak, &amp; the God of Jacob.</hi> Hence <hi>Mat:</hi> 22.29, 30. <hi>Chriſt proves the Reſurrection by conſequence</hi> the ſumm whereof is, as if he had ſaid, that which God ſpake to Moſes in the Buſh, inferreth the whole perſons of <hi>Abraham Iſaak</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> to be in everlaſting covenant with him, and that they ſhall be bleſſed: therefore there ſhall be a Reſurrection. For how can the body be glorified, except it riſe again? and ſo farr were the hearers from objecting againſt this kind of argumentation as that they highly approved of it. One of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> having heard their reaſoning, perceived that he had anſwered them well. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.28. <hi>Then certain of the Scribes, anſwering ſaid, Master thou haſt anſwered well.</hi> Luke 20.39. <hi>The multitude were aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his doctrine.</hi> Mat: 22.42. <hi>And no man was able to anſwer him, neither durſt any man (from that time forth) aske him any more queſtions verſe</hi> 46. Out of Pſalm 16.10. <hi>Peter proves the Reſurrection of Christ.</hi> Act. 2.31. <hi>He</hi> that is, <hi>the Patriark David ſeeing this before ſpake of the Reſerrection of Christ, that his ſoul was not loſt in hell, neither his fleſh did ſee corruption.</hi> Yet the Pſalmiſt in theſe words ſpeakes not of the Reſurrection in expreſs termes, but onely by conſequence, the queſtion is; whether the believing Galatians, which were formerly heathens, were juſtifyed by faith? Paul out of thoſe words <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.18. <hi>And in thy ſeed, ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſſed;</hi> proveth the affirmative by conſequence. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 8, 9: The queſtion is: whether believing <hi>Abraham</hi> hath matter of glorying before God? The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> from Gen: 15.6. <hi>concludeth the negative by conſequence. Rom:</hi> 4.2, 3. Queſtion: whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> did well, or blaſphemed, in ſaying that he was God? <hi>Chr ſt</hi> from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.6. juſtifieth his act by a Scripture conſequence. <hi>Io n</hi> 10.35, 36. His argument proceeds from the leſs to the greater.</p>
                  <p>Queſtion: whether <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is neceſſary unto the believing Gentiles? The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> concludeth the negative by conſequence. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.8, 9. <hi>God bare them witneſs, giving them the Holy-Ghoſt, even as he did unto us, and put no difference between them &amp; us, purifying their hearts by faith.</hi> Therefore &amp;c: Many more inſtances are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible, if need were. So many citations as there are in the New Teſtament, of teſtim onies in the old Teſtament not extant there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171454:7"/>
in expreſs termes, are ſo many proofes of the Scripture-conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences. <hi>Scripture trueths by conſequence are called Scripture: yee do erre not knowing the Scripture. Mat.</hi> 22.29. <hi>for what ſaith the Scripture;</hi> Rom. 4.3. <hi>and the Scripture foreſeeing</hi> Gala. 3.8. what Peter deduceth from <hi>Davids</hi> words by conſequence that he affirmeth <hi>David</hi> to have ſaid. <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.31. what <hi>Paul</hi> deduceth out of <hi>Moſes</hi> by juſt conſequence, that he affirmeth <hi>Moſes</hi> to have ſaid <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5.10.</p>
                  <p>That propoſition; <hi>the Scripture is a perfect Rule of life.</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as including <hi>Scripture-conſequences?</hi> otherwiſe, it were not a trueth. The greateſt part of Scripture-trueth is revealed in Scripture-conſequences. Yea many fundamentall trueths are not held forth in expreſs termes, but by manifeſt conſequence.</p>
                  <p>If there be no truth contained in the Scripture, but what is held forth therein in expreſs termes: then the individuall perſons of <hi>Thomas &amp; Mary,</hi> &amp;c, are therein neither Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded Obedience, nor forbidden diſobedience. For we no where read thou Thomas or Mary, ſuch an one by name, do this, or not that. This trueth concerning Scripture-conſequences is the more to be attended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the time, wherein many after the example of <hi>Arrius</hi> of old, and the <hi>Libertines, &amp; Gunter</hi> with ſome other Jeſuites of late, when they are not able to anſwer unto Scripture-arguments; rather then to yeild unto the trueth, chuſe to fly to this miſerable ſubterfuge of hereticks namely that the trueth defended againſt them is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Scripture, becauſe it is not there in expreſs termes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Concerning the Vindication of ſome Scriptures.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.9. <hi>That was the true light, which lighteneth every man, that commeth into the world.</hi> Hence they affirme <hi>that in every man</hi> Collectively, <hi>i. e.</hi> in all men, not one excepted; <hi>there is a light,</hi> which being followed is an infallible guide: &amp; that this <hi>light within us, &amp; not the Scripture, or written word, is the Rule of life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In anſwer hereunto, two things are to be cleared, Firſt, that the ſence of the text pretended: is notoriouſly falſe. Secondly what is the ſence of the place.</p>
                  <p>Were the ſence pretended ſound, then <hi>righteouſnes ſhould be by the law, not with ſtanding ſin; contrary to. Rom.</hi> 8.3. For the light which is in every man that is born into the world, is not <hi>Goſpel-light.</hi> The Goſpel being the ſecret of God, a myſtery un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171454:8"/>
to <hi>Angels, &amp; Adam</hi> himſelf in the time of innocency. <hi>The naturall man cannot know the things of the spirit of God</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.14. Natural is to be conſtrued in oppoſition to ſpiritual: and denoteth a man, as following the dictate of reaſon only, or the light of nature, whence it is manifeſt, that the <hi>light of nature,</hi> as ſuch: and <hi>the light of the spirit,</hi> are contra-diſtinct; the one to the other. The light of nature, remaining in <hi>Adams</hi> poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſince the lapſe: is ſo little, as that it is not to be mentioned the ſame day, with what was in <hi>Adam,</hi> before the fall. The light of nature, conſiſts in common principles imprinted upon the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul, by nature: inclining man, to aſſent unto ſome na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and manifeſt trueths upon the repreſentation of them; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out waiting for any proofe; that is, as it were by inſtinct, without argument. Viz: <hi>that it is impoſſible for the ſame things, at once, for to be, &amp; not to be: that the whole, is greater then the part. That a man is bound, not to do to others, what he would not have done unto himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As alſo in certain <hi>Notions:</hi> that <hi>there is a God, that God is to be worſhipped,</hi> that <hi>Parents are to be honoured,</hi> that <hi>there is difference to be made between that which is good, and that which is bad. That we ought not to ly, steale &amp;c:</hi> In reference whereunto, men are ſaid to have a natural <hi>Conſcience bearing witneſs unto their actions, and their thoughts to be accuſing or excuſing. Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. The uſe is, Firſt, to be a help whence they <hi>might ſeek after God. Acts</hi> 17.27. by meanes hereof ſome have arrived at the diſcovery that <hi>there is but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>one God,</hi> that he is an act, void of all paſſive qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, yea hereby they aſcend ſo farr: as to diſcover ſome of his attributes, viz <hi>his Eternity, Omnipotency, &amp; being the Creator.</hi> For thus much may be known of God to them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19, 20.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>To leave them inexcuſable:</hi> in that they walk not anſwerable to the light of nature.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dem natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra vi rationis hominem conciliat ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mini &amp; ad orationis, et ad vitae ſoci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etaten. Cicero lib 1 de Officijs. Auguſt. Epiſ 105.</note> 
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 1.20. 3. <hi>For the preſervation of humane ſociety.</hi> Their principles ſpeculative, riſe higher then their priniples practicall. Yet their Principles practical, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deportment towards God, are more obſcure, then thoſe which relate to their behaviour towards man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their knowledg, as to that which is ſaving, is but folly. <hi>Where is the Scribe, where is the diſputer, hath not</hi> God <hi>made fooliſh the wiſedome of this world?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.20. Hence the times of Gentiliſm, are called <hi>times of ignorance,</hi> Acts 17.30. <hi>Of wrath,</hi> Rom: 1.18. <hi>Without</hi> God, <hi>&amp; without hope,</hi> Eph. 2.12. <hi>The Lord looked down
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171454:8"/>
from heaven upon the Children of men to ſee if there were any that did underſtand &amp; ſeek God. There is none that underſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh after God, they are all gone out of the way, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.2.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 53.2.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9.10 Moreover this little light that there is, is much miſcarried, whileſt it is managed by the reigning influence of the power of darkneſs the Judgement is corrupt as well as the will, whoſe corruption perverts the exerciſe of the faculty of reaſon. <hi>They became vaine in their reaſonings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. To conclude: the light of nature notwithſtanding, the irregenerate man is darkneſse.</p>
                  <p>Star-light, cannot make it, otherwiſe then night. The light of nature ſince the fall, compared with the light of the image of God, before the fall, hath not the proportion of Star-light, to the bright Sun-light at noon-day. This indeed is but darkneſs. But, if compared with the light of the Goſpell, it is worſe then groſs darkneſs. <hi>Yee were darkneſs</hi> Eph. 5.8. <hi>Alienated from the life of</hi> God <hi>through the ignorance that is in them</hi> Ephe. 4.18. <hi>Behold all ye that kindle a fire, that compaſs your ſelves about with sparkes: walk in the light of your fire, and in the sparkes that ye have kindled, this ſhall ye have of mine hand, ye ſhall ly down in ſorrow</hi> Iſaiah. 50.11.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>— Quantâ ſub nocte, jacebat</l>
                     <l>noſtra dies? —</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Concerning the ſenſe of the place: diſtinguiſh 1. Of <hi>the light,</hi> where by we are enlightned. 2. Of the <hi>light enlightning.</hi> 3. Of <hi>every man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>light,</hi> whereby wee are <hi>inlightened: it is either the light of nature &amp; of right reaſon:</hi> or, the <hi>light of ſaving grace. The light inlightening:</hi> is either the <hi>WORD,</hi> i: e. <hi>The Sonn conſidered onely as the ſecond perſon, not incarnate: or Christ,</hi> i e. <hi>the ſonn conſidered as incarnate.</hi> This phraſe <hi>[Every man]</hi> is taken <hi>collectively?</hi> for all men that come into the world, abſolutely, none excepted. Or <hi>diſtributively,</hi> for all men ſo qualified, of all ſorts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calvin, Beza, Piſcator,</hi> and others, underſtand theſe words <hi>[every man]</hi> collectively, by the light wherewith we are enlightened, <hi>The light of Reaſon,</hi> and look at this light of reaſon, as an effect proceeding from the WORD: <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Sonn,</hi> conſidered as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſon. But as concerning man, endued only with the light remaining in him ſince the fall: they conclude him to be darkneſs and unable to comprehend the light, ſo; as to improve it to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171454:9"/>
They are ſo farr from affirming this light, to be the <hi>light of life,</hi> as they are from denying <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be the <hi>light of life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others, underſtand <hi>[Every man] distributively,</hi> by the light wherewith we are <hi>enlightened,</hi> the light of ſaving grace, or Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: and look at this light of Saving grace, as an effect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from <hi>Christ,</hi> i.e. <hi>the Son incarnate.</hi> That phraſe <hi>[every man]</hi> is illuſtrated by <hi>Pſal:</hi> 145.14. <hi>The Lord upholdeth all that fall: and rayſeth up all that be bowed down.</hi> The meaning is not, that <hi>ALL</hi> that fall, are upholden by the Lord: but, that ALL amongſt thoſe which fall, who are upholden: are upholden by the Lord.</p>
                  <p>It is an uſual ſpeech, to attribute all thoſe deeds unto God, which none can do, but God. Both interpretations have many authors and are analogous unto Scriptures, which of them is genuine, is left free to the judgment of the Reader.</p>
                  <p>Jer: 31.34. Heb: 8.11. <hi>And they ſhall teach no more, every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying know the Lord: for they ſhall all know mee, from the leaſt of them, unto the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord</hi> Hence it is inferred, that there is no need of the miniſtry of man, under the times of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, that the times here ſpoken of, are the times <hi>after thoſe dayes Jer:</hi> 3.33. <hi>Heb:</hi> 8.11. <hi>viz:</hi> the times, after the dayes of the <hi>Moſaical adminiſtration,</hi> of the Covenant of Grace: which expired fully, at the Paſſion of Chriſt, ſo, that the times here ſpoken of, are the times of the Goſpel-diſpenſation of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace: beginning at the abrogation of the <hi>Moſaical-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation,</hi> and continuing, untill time ſhall be no more.</p>
                  <p>But what more diſconſonant from, or what more contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory to Scripture, then to teach, that throughout all the time of the Goſpel-diſpenſation, there is no need of the miniſtry of man? wee appeal to the examples of the <hi>Apostles, Evangeliſts, Ordinary Office-labourers</hi> in the word &amp; doctrine, and Goſpel-churches recorded in ſacred writt; as alſo to the inſtitution of the Goſpel-miniſtry, by <hi>Pastors and Teachers,</hi> for the calling of the Elect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Nations, <hi>for the perfecting of the ſaints, untill we come unto a perfect man;</hi> i. e. untill the perfection, of the Myſtical body of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Jer: 31.31,—34. We have an illuſtrious compariſon, between the external Covenant of Grace, made with the National Iſrael, in the time of <hi>Moſes:</hi> and the internal Covenant of Grace, made
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171454:9"/>
with the elect <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the time of the Goſpel. As alſo, the ſecond covenant (other reſpect of its preheminence omitted, not ſo nextly pertinent to the preſent discuſſion) preferred before the firſt, upon the account of the betterneſs of the diſcriminating promiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They</hi> i. e. the national Iſrael <hi>brake the covenant although</hi> God <hi>was an huſband unto them.</hi> But as concerning the elect Iſrael under the better covenant <hi>I will put my law in their inward parts and write it in their hearts, I will be their</hi> God, <hi>and they ſhall be my people, ſaith the LORD.</hi> which is in effect the ſame with <hi>Iſay</hi> 54 13, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.45. <hi>And they ſhall be all taught of GOD</hi> i.e. They ſhall not be onely taught of man, as others in externall covenant onely are. Theſe words <hi>[They ſhall be all taught of GOD]</hi> are not to be interpreted <hi>excluſively ſo as to exclude the teaching of man:</hi> but <hi>exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively,</hi> ſo <hi>as to include the teaching alſo of God:</hi> witneſs the cloud of Scripture-inſtances of all thoſe under the Goſpel-diſpenſation, who were taught of God: but how? by not without the teaching of man. Further the promiſe undertakes for ſuch a writing of the Law in their hearts ſuch a teaching of God, as that they ſhall not finally apoſtate from the Covenant: Jer: 32.40. <hi>But I will put my Fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Subject ſpoken of, are ſuch perſons, which are actually the people of God, ſuch in whoſe hearts the Law is written. <hi>The knowledg of God,</hi> is taken either for that knowledg of him, which is eſſential to effectual vocation or for the knowledg of edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Taking knowledg in the former notion, of <hi>writing the Law in the heart</hi> indelebly: this being a property of the Covenant of grace, the ſenſe naturally flowes, <hi>viz:</hi> that after converſion once wrought, there ſhall be no need, to ſpeak unto ſuch, to know the Lord: namely with a knowledg eſſential to vocation, as if they were ignorant thereof, for this were in effect to deny, a characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtical priviledg of the Covenant, and to affirm falling from grace. Regeneration is not iterable, they who are once converted, need not to be converted from the ſtate of nature to the ſtate of grace a ſecond time. This ſeemeth to be the genuine ſenſe of the place.</p>
                  <p>If we take knowledg in the latter notion, <hi>viz:</hi> for <hi>the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of edification;</hi> then the interpretation proceeds comparatively, thus: comparing the <hi>Gospel-Iſrael,</hi> having the law written in their hearts, being alſo under a clearer diſpenſation, &amp; under the promiſe of an efficacious, &amp; copious influence of the Spirit: with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171454:10"/>
                     <hi>National-Iſrael,</hi> finally impenitent under the Law, the teachers of the one, as to a great part of the labour of their miniſtry, in reſpect of the conſolatory ſucceſs thereof, eſpecially in the glorious times; ſhall not look upon it as labour, compared with the fruitleſs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the other, ſo as the forementioned <hi>Goſpel-hearers,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the premiſes, might ſeem rather, comparatively to have been taught by ſome immediate irradiation, then by meanes of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary inſtruction. 1 John 2.27. <hi>But the annointing which ye have received of him abideth in you: and you need not that any man teach you: but as the ſame annointing teacheth you of all things, and is no ly.</hi> Hence it is inferred, that believers have no need of being taught by man. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Objector miſtakes the queſtion. The Apoſtle ſpeakes of heterodox doctrine taught by man. The objection proceeeds concerning teaching by man. The ſenſe of the words alledged is, you believers, who through grace, are an<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ointed with the in dwelling, ſaving operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; efficatious influence of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is <hi>the only Teacher:</hi> have ſo learned Chriſt, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Lords Chriſt, that you need not be troubled with, nor ought you to harken to, the doctrine of <hi>Cerinthius, Ebton,</hi> or the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> who though they pretend themſelves to be teachers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are indeed <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. So teaching Chriſt, as that they <hi>un-Chriſt Chriſt:</hi> nor have you need of any other doctrine whatſoever from any other man, not agreeable unto the doctrine of the true <hi>Chriſt</hi> which, you who are annointed, have received.</p>
                  <p>2 Pet: 1.19. <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of Propheſy, where unto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, untill the day dawn, and the day-starr ariſe in your hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence is inferred. that after the reception of the Spirit, or believing there is no more need to attend unto the Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This interpretation preſuppoſeth three things, any where of failing, it cannot ſtand. 1. That we are to underſtand by a <hi>ſure word of Prophecie:</hi> the <hi>whole Scripture.</hi> 2. By <hi>the day dawning, and the day-starr ariſing:</hi> the <hi>Spirit of grace in Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 3. By the particle <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill:</hi> the <hi>limited inſtant of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Before which, though we either do, or may, yet after which we are not to attend unto the Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf expounds the <hi>word of prophecie</hi> verſe 19, of the <hi>Scripture</hi> of the old Teſtament <hi>verſe</hi> 20, 21. Which Scripture-teſtimony compared with the <hi>verbal teſtimony</hi> of the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171454:10"/>
the <hi>voyce heard in the holy mount,</hi> in relation to the doctrine of Chriſt: he preferreth <hi>(not as the moſt true, but,)</hi> as the <hi>moſt ſure ground for Faith</hi> of the two, and upon this account: becauſe the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal teſtimony of the Apoſtles, though Apoſtolical, was as yet but verbal. and not ſcriptural. So that ſhould this text (upon a falſe ſuppoſition) be looked at as ſpeaking of a believers non-attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto Scripture, yet it proceeds not concerning the Scripture in general, but concerning the Scripture of the old teſtament only, not of the Canon of the new Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>day dawning,</hi> and <hi>the day-starr appearing:</hi> denotes either the ſaying light of the Spirit, making our attention unto the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from time to time effectual, during the ſeaſon of our depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance hereupon, throughout this life: or that day-light of the viſion of glory: both which ſenſes in concluſion iſſue in one. But, it cannot be underſtood of the regenerating-light of the Spirit; becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeakes to thoſe who are believers, ſtill to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the Scripture.</p>
                  <p>The particle <hi>[untill]</hi> (any other acception not pertinent to the matter under conſideration omitted) either noteth a certain time, before which ſuch a thing is to be, which was not before: or after which ſuch a thing is not to be, which was before. <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Judah, nor a Law-giver from between his feet, untill Shiloh come.</hi> Gen: 49.10. But here it denoteth not any certain time in this life, after which we are not to attend upon the word written. For then, that certain time notified by the <hi>day dawning</hi> and <hi>the day-starr appearing:</hi> muſt either relate to Chriſts comming in the fleſh, or to the beginning of the Goſpel-diſpenſation, or to the effectual revelation of Chriſt in vocation, or to ſome other terme, that may rationally and ſcripturally be inſtanced in: but it cannot relate unto the firſt, becauſe it is not <hi>an appearance in the fleſh,</hi> but an <hi>appearance in the heart,</hi> that is here expreſly ſpoken of: and <hi>the day-starr ariſe in your HEARTS.</hi> Neither indeed, can it relate either unto the firſt or any other of the termes, or limits mentioned: becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> writes unto ſuch, ſtill to <hi>attend upon the word of Prophecie,</hi> who were regenerate; who were believers: <hi>have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obteined like precious faith with himſelf, Cap:</hi> 1.1. Yea ſuch, who cannot be looked at otherwiſe, then of conſiderable ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; proficiency in the faith: and lived after his incarnation, and Goſpel-diſpenſation: whence, were this Objection of force, it would
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171454:11"/>
follow, that this exhortation of the Apoſtle had then been as much after its time, as that <hi>terme</hi> of a believers attention unto the <hi>word of prophecy,</hi> be it either the incarnation, Goſpel-diſpenſation, or regeneration of thoſe; whom he puts upon this duty, was before this time. The Goſpel (whether any of it were now written or not) was promulged by Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, and therefore was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging. If the particle <hi>untill</hi> bee ſayd to denote a certaine terme, not in this life, but relating unto the <hi>dawning and riſing</hi> of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of glory: the queſtion is graunted, and the objection falleth.</p>
                  <p>While the Church <hi>is in a darke place,</hi> the light of the Scripture is to be attended unto: hence the written word is here compared <hi>unto a light that ſhineth in a darke place</hi> now wee know, that there is much darkneſs, and obſcurity in the hearts of all the Children of light, in this life. 1 <hi>Corin:</hi> 13.9.</p>
                  <p>Or; the particle <hi>untill</hi> ſignifyeth a terme, iſsuing in attayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the good, attainable in ſuch a way. or in the participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the perfecting end, of the ſubject, ſpoken of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A bruiſed read ſhall hee, not break, and ſmoaking flax ſhall hee not quench,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>untill he ſend forth judgment unto victory. Mat:</hi> 12.21.</p>
                  <p>This notion agreeth not only with the analogie of faith, but alſo according to the mind of the Apoſtles common action ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatory, ſeemeth more readily to flow. The ſcope of <hi>Peter,</hi> is to confirm the hearts of the <hi>twelve tribes ſcattered abroad,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the trueth of the Goſpel: this he doth by two arguments, The firſt taken from the teſtimony of the Apoſtles <hi>verſe</hi> 15 16, 17. The ſecond, from the word of Prophecy: illuſtrated by two adjuncts, the former of its <hi>ſureneſs:</hi> the latter of our <hi>taking heed thereunto:</hi> this attention he amplifyeth, by calling unto ſuch a conſcientious and vigorous continuance therin; as may never be <hi>in vain in the Lord,</hi> yea ſuch as that the effectual light of the ſpirit of grace concurring with the doctrinal light of the word: may from duty to duty, ſhine upon the dark places of their hearts more and more, untill the dawning of the perfect day of the viſion of glory.</p>
                  <p>If with ſome Orthodox Interpreters, wee underſtand by a <hi>dark place,</hi> the time of the Church under the old Teſtament: compared with the night, wherein candles are lighted: and by the <hi>day-dawning,</hi> the time of the Goſpel day-light, wherin the Sun ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; the new Teſtament expounding the old, and thereby giving a greater light.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:171454:11"/>Yet ſtill we are to keep in mind, that as the New Teſtament giveth light unto the Old, ſo the Old Teſtament giveth light unto the New: they give light mutually one unto another. Tis the ſame <hi>Christ,</hi> &amp; the ſame <hi>Gospel,</hi> which is held forth both in the old &amp; in the New Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: <hi>Heb:</hi> 13.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. As the trueths of the old Teſtament, are confirmed by the New: ſo what more frequent then the confirmation of the New Teſtament, from the Old: both by Chriſt and his Apoſtles? The word <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill,</hi> doth not here intend a certain time, whereat they were diſcharged from after attention, to the word of Prophecie: as if they who were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for their attention hitherto, were now diſmiſſed therefrom and ſtood not from henceforth obliged any more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gen:</hi> 28.15. <hi>For I will not leave thee, untill I have done that which I have spoken to thee of,</hi> 2 Sam: 6.23. <hi>Therefore Michal, the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Saul had no child unto [or untill] the day of her death,</hi> Mat: 16 28. <hi>They ſhall not taſt of death, untill they ſee the Kingdome of God.</hi> It were ill gathered from hence, either that God did forſake Jacob after he had performed that promiſe concerning his ſafe return. Or, that Michal had a child after the day of her death. Or, that the Diſciples which ſaw his glory in the Mount, ſhould not out-live the Aſſenſion, Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, and the promulgation of the Goſpel to the Gentiles, with ſignes enſuing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mat:</hi> 11.13. <hi>For all the Prophets and the Law prophecyed untill John.</hi> Mat: 22.44. <hi>Sit thou at my right hand, untill I make thine enemyes thy footſtoole.</hi> John 5.17. <hi>My Father worketh hitherto, or [untill now,] and I work.</hi> 1 Tim: 4.13. <hi>Till I come, give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In his exem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pris. prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eri tam ita nega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rat, ut contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> non ſignifice<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur.</note> It cannot be gathered from hence, either that after <hi>John,</hi> there is no more Law and Prophets. Or, that after <hi>Christs</hi> enemyes are ſubdued, he ſhall ſit no longer at the right hand of his Father. Or, that after <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpake thoſe words, the Fathers Governing-providence of the world ceaſed. Or, that after <hi>Pauls</hi> comming, <hi>Timothy</hi> is no more to attend to reading, exhortation, and preaching.</p>
                  <p>In the Negative examples, the word <hi>untill</hi> ſo inferreth the denyall of a thing, concerning the time before it: as that, it doth not at all inferr the affirmative of that thing concerning the time after it. In the affirmative examples, the word <hi>untill</hi> ſo inferreth the affirmative of a thing, concerning the time before, as that, it not at all infers the denyal of that thing, concerning the time after it</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171454:12"/>The ſumme is according to this laſt interpretation the word <hi>untill</hi> is taken <hi>extenſively not excluſively.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So farr then, is this text from diſobliging believers, from their attendance upon the Scriptures: as that, it is a moſt ſolemn &amp; ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous incentive, as of all others to whom the ſacred Canon ſhall be revealed: ſo alſo, of believers in particular, not only to attend upon the word of prophecie, or the Scripture: but ſo to take heed thereunto, as that their attention, through the co-operation of the Spirit, may be effectual: and that ſo long as their hearts are dark places, <hi>i. e.</hi> during their preſent ſtate of imperfection: untill <hi>Chriſt the bright morning-starr appear</hi> in their ſoules; according to the fulneſs of the Spirit of grace, and the noon-day-light of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The heterodoxie &amp; errour of ſuch, who from the text alledged, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr the old Teſtament to be unneceſſary unto thoſe that live under the Goſpel: is argued thus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Promiſes, given unto the Saints in the old Teſtament belong unto believers living under the new Teſtament. The Promiſe made unto <hi>Joſhua Joſh.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp; to David Pſal.</hi> 118.6. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews are led by the hand unto &amp; taught confidently to make uſe of, in reference unto their preſent, and Perſonal caſes. <hi>For he hath ſaid I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> So that we viz: <hi>believers</hi> under the Goſpel, &amp; not onely David, may boldly ſay, the <hi>Lord is my helper, I will not feare what man ſhall do unto mee.</hi> The trueths held forth by the Prophets, touching ſalvation by <hi>Christ:</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not onely thoſe, who lived in the times of the old, but alſo us; who live in the times of the new Teſtament. 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.10, 11, 12. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom it was revealed, that not unto themſelves, but unto us, they did miniſter the things which are now reported unto you.</hi> The exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary juſtification of <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, is written in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our ſakes. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.23, 24. <hi>Now it was not written for his ſake alone, that it was imputed to him: but; for us alſo, to whom it ſhall be imputed, if we believe in him that rayſed up Jeſus our Lord from the dead. The examples of the old Teſtament, are written for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, upon whom the ends of the world are come</hi> 1 Cor: 10.11. Not now to labour further in the proof hereof, by an induction of particulars: the uſefulneſs of the old Teſtament to thoſe that live under the New, we haue aſſerted once for all; and that, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that part of Sacred writt. <hi>Rom:</hi> 15.4. <hi>For whatſoever things
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171454:12"/>
were written afore time, were written for our learning: that wee through patience, and comfort of the Scripture might have hope. John</hi> 5.39. <hi>The Jewes in the time of Chriſt,</hi> are Commanded <hi>to ſearch the Scripture,</hi> which neceſſarily proceeds of the Scriptures of the old Teſtament, the new, as then not being extant. After the time of <hi>Christ</hi> we hear the Teſtimony of the new Teſtament, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the profitableneſs of the Old. 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs: that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good workes.</hi> Underſtand this, as ſpoken of the holy Scriptures, known by <hi>Timothy of a child,</hi> which muſt neceſſarily be the Old Teſtament.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the Signal Nature of the Quakers, and other falſe Teachers, ariſing, and prevailing among the people of God.</head>
               <p>AS the Soveraigne Lord, and onely wiſe God, is both the diſpoſer and interpreter: So hath he given unto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, to be diſcerners of the times. The Scriptures held forth many occurrents of providence Significative of the ſtate of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, &amp; of the reſpective condition of the profeſſion thereof: as alſo of Gods more remarkable adminiſtration unto his people, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with relation unto his Predictions, permiſſive, or comminatory or both, Hence we read of <hi>ſignes of the times. Mat:</hi> 16.3. Of <hi>good times</hi> in the place cited. Of <hi>evill times, Mat:</hi> 24.33. This trueth, the Pſalmiſt mentions, as of acknowledg'd &amp; notable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Pſal. 74.9. <hi>We ſee not our ſignes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The not <hi>diſcerning</hi> herof, as it is a matter of blame: but <hi>how is it ye diſcern not this time? Luke.</hi> 12.56. So in the diſcerning thereof, is a matter of praiſe. And the Children of <hi>Iſſachar which</hi> were <hi>men which had underſtanding of the time, to know what Jſrael ought to do:</hi> The heads, of them were two hundred, and all their brethren were at their Commandement 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.32. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortative unto the good, &amp; awing unto the bad, was that ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble word of an <hi>Ancient,</hi> who when terror had ſurpriſed the hearts of thouſands by reaſon of that fearfull earth-quake, which in <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time threw up the very foundation of the temple, then about to be reedified by the <hi>Apoſtate-Emperour;</hi> told them, that this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing &amp; ſtrange accident to them was but the accompliſhment of that prophecie. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, there ſhall not be left here, one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171454:13"/>
ſtone upon another that ſhall not be thrown down.</hi> Full of preſence of Spirit in a time of Calamity, was that ſpeech, where with <hi>Lupus a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhop</hi> is reported to have greeted the enemy <hi>Attilas,</hi> then depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulating &amp; laying waſt his countrey: <hi>I rejoyce</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that you are come ſafe, whom I judge to be the ſcourge of the Lord, &amp; of my God, ſent to chaſtiſe his people.</hi> The good man; howſoever others hearts might faile under their fears both of preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, &amp; of everlaſting burnings: looking at the King of the <hi>Hunnes,</hi> not as <hi>a weapon of deſtruction,</hi> according to his own deſire; but as <hi>a rod of correction,</hi> in the hand of God: and chooſing affliction, rather then iniquity, gathers <hi>meat out of the eater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Falſe Teachers, and falſe Prophets are ſignal; <hi>i. e,</hi> they are ſignes, that the time is come, when God will inflict vindicative ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual-juſtice; upon the <hi>non-receivers of the Trueth in the love of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are executioners of ſpiritual juſtice, puniſhing the <hi>non-recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the trueth:</hi> with deception by their lyes. They are inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental executioners of Juſtice, to puniſh the non-reception of the trueth, diſpenſed by the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> with <hi>deception by, and reception of a ly,</hi> diſſeminated by the miniſters of Satan.</p>
               <p>This ſolemn, and by reaſon to the iniquity of the times) both awfull, and ſeaſonable trueth: the Reader is deſired the rather to attend the proof of. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> beſides other ſinners, laden with the guilt of the eſcape of a blaſphemous <hi>Syrian;</hi> rejects the trueth in the mouth of <hi>Micaiah, the Lords Prophet,</hi> diſwading him from going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ramoth-Gilead:</hi> This; God viſited, by giving him up <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a ly in the mouth of the falſe Prophets;</hi> commiſſioned to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him, to go to <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> unto his deſtruction.</p>
               <p>1 Kings 22.19,-23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am come in my Fathers name, and ye receive me not: if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall come in his own name, him ye will receive.</hi> John 5.43. The awfull trueth contained in this text, will be the better ſeen, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving it into four propoſitions. 1. <hi>Chriſt</hi> came unto ſinners <hi>i. e.</hi> tendered himſelf to them, according to the Covenant of grace and that according to the appointment of the Father: an external unparallelled mercy. <hi>But laſt of all he ſent unto them his Son: ſaying, ſurely they will reverence my Son.</hi> 2. They <hi>received not the Son, though ſent unto them in the Fathers name.</hi> As the Goſpell is the great command; ſo the rejection of the Goſpel, is the great ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If I had not come, and ſpoken unto them they, had not had ſinn: but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171454:13"/>
now they have no cloak for their ſin. John</hi> 15.22. 3. Upon the rejecting of the Doctrine of the great <hi>Teacher,</hi> there are <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> ſuppoſed to <hi>come in their own name. A famine of the word of trueth</hi> is a ſore judgment. <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11. But theſe teachers, are worſe then no teachers. Accurſed &amp; ominous. 4. That thoſe who <hi>received not Chriſt, comming in his Fathers name, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive teachers comming in their own name.</hi> No better <hi>Teacher,</hi> no ſuch <hi>teacher,</hi> no other <hi>teacher,</hi> then he was whom they refuſed.</p>
               <p>Scarce any (if any) worſe <hi>teachers</hi> then thoſe whom they received. Tis not ſo ready to ſay, whether their unbelief or belief was more dreadfull. Wofull is their condition, when the <hi>teacher</hi> is accurſed <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.9. and the hearer bewitched <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhall believe a ly: that they all might be damned, who believed not the trueth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.11, 12. See here the non-<hi>receivers of the trueth in the love of it,</hi> puniſhed both with a penal, and effectual miſſion of deceivers.</p>
               <p>That this tremendous diſpenſation, may have the deeper impreſſion upon our hearts: we find the Vindictive hand of God upon the contempt of the Goſpel, mentioned thrice in one chapter: and that alſo, ſometime as a forerunner of the deſtruction of a nation. <hi>Mat:</hi> 24.5. <hi>For many ſhall come in my name, ſaying I am Chriſt.</hi> Falſe teachers ſhall come, and leſt any ſhould think their comming notwithſtanding, happily they ſhall not prevail: it is added, <hi>and ſhall deceive many.</hi> Again, verſe 11. <hi>Many falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſhall ariſe.</hi> Forget not again what followeth, <hi>and ſhall deceive many.</hi> So verſe 24. <hi>For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes &amp; wonders: in ſo much; that if it were poſſible, they ſhould deceive the very Elect.</hi> Hereunto (if with ſome learned interpreters, we underſtand by the <hi>end</hi> mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Mat:</hi> 24. that famous period &amp; deſtruction of the Nation of the Jewes) we may not unaptly annex that of the Apoſtle 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. in the judgment of ſome as atteſting unto <hi>Mat:</hi> 24.3, 6, 33, 34 Namely that theſe grand-deceivers were fore-runners of the then enſuing miſery of that nation. <hi>Little children, it is the laſt time, &amp; as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now there are many Antichriſts, whereby we know that it is the laſt time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumm is; that the <hi>doctrines of Devils</hi> audaciouſly diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by numerous falſe teachers, pretending themſelves to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171454:14"/>
immediately ſent of God, are <hi>SIGNAL,</hi> or are ſignes of evill times, in four reſpects, <hi>i. e.</hi> They ſignifie four things
<list>
                     <item>1. Greater light then Ordinary foregoing.</item>
                     <item>2. The non-reception of that light by many, in the love of it.</item>
                     <item>3. The Judicial giving up of many <hi>non-recivers of the Trueth in the love of it to believe their lyes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Sometimes at leaſt, alſo a National Calamity impending: when the prementioned iniquities, are in Conjunction with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crying ſinns without Repentance.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Sinning againſt the Goſpel, is very ſinfull. The Goſpel is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution or effect <hi>tempered of the Grace of God, and the blood of Chriſt</hi> ingredients, neither of which are to be found in the Law. So much as the Goſpel excelleth the Law, ſo much is <hi>ſinning againſt the Goſpel</hi> aggravated compared with <hi>ſinning againſt the Law</hi> Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the Goſpel is yet heightned by circumſtances: that it is given to us after the tranſgreſſion of the Law. Given to ſome tranſgreſſors, and not unto others. Of them to whom it is given, diſpenſed with greater light to ſome, then to others. What Nation gloryed in theſe priviledges above our own, our ſelves being witneſſes? From the kind of ſinning; If the non-recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the trueth in the love of it, expoſeth unto this vindictive deception, according to what dreadfull degree ſhall they be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed obnoxious, who perſevere in ſcandals under the light?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Count it pleaſure to riot in the day time,</hi> yea fear not to <hi>commit that abomination in Iſrael, of turning the grace of God into wantonneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the doctrine of free grace, drawing a licence to ſin, to take their fill of luſt: and that without the guilt of ſin, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſin, yea with a pretended conſcience of obedience.</p>
               <p>In a word, <hi>to feaſt the old man unto the higheſt, with the blood of Jeſus,</hi> and compleat <hi>the mystery of iniquity, by the myſtery of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the non-reception of the trueth of the Goſpel, is a fearfull ſin, ſo the fruit thereof is a fearfull evill. Their unbelief is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: their belief is fearfull. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief of the trueth is iniquity: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a ly, is both iniquity &amp; folly.</hi> The trueth they unbelieve, is a trueth of the greateſt wiſdom. The ly which they believe is an object of the greateſt vanity. To believe the trueth, is a great mercy. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.25. <hi>At one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord, to be faithfull.</hi> To believe a deſtructively, is a great judgment. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:171454:14"/>
2.11, 12. <hi>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a ly, that they all might be damned, who believed not the truth.</hi> Not to believe <hi>Christ</hi> is to make him an <hi>Impoſtor:</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable is divine juſtice, that the iſſue of ſuch unbelief, ſhould be the believing of Impoſtors. So legible is divine juſtice, in that they who forſake the <hi>way of ſalvation, ſhould chooſe the way of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> that the folly of that wiſdom may be manifeſt, whoſe wiſdom is to diſacknowledg the Wiſdom of God; and that the glory of that wiſdom may be ever adored, the contempt wherof, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the contemners unto ſuch finall folly.</p>
               <p>Theſe lying Spirits, with other like <hi>Pests,</hi> howſoever incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable &amp; deſpicable looked at as in themſelves: yet if looked at as meſſengers of Divine wrath, witneſſes of guilt, and impenitence inſtruments of penalty, and commiſſionated to do effectual execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they are now repreſented under a formidable aſpect: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come objects of great terrour. God can plague <hi>Egypt</hi> with <hi>lice,</hi> and make <hi>locusts, wormes, &amp; graſhoppers,</hi> a matter of horror unto <hi>Judah: though there remained but wounded men amongſt the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans: yet ſhould they riſe up every man in his tent, &amp; burne this Citty with fire.</hi> Alas tis ſin that armes juſtice, and diſarmes the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. When there is a concurrence of delinquency and authority, the meanneſs of the executioner aggravates, not extenuates the anguiſh of the malefactor. What more formidable then a penall and vindictive-permiſſion, of a deluſion-deſtructive: Upon Gods willing the permiſſion of ſin, ſin falleth out infallibly. Upon this antecedent <hi>Adam</hi> when all mankind was conteined in that one man yet in innocency, is deceived &amp; ſinneth away, not only the Image of God from his poſterity, but alſo ſinneth mankind into the guilt of eternal death. <hi>The woman which thou gaveſt to be with me, gave mee of the tree and I did eat.</hi> Upon a permiſſion penal-corrective, <hi>Peter</hi> falleth as ſhamefully before the temptation of a poor maid, as he engaged confidently. No merveil then if upon a permiſſion penal-vindictive foregoing, we read; <hi>and all that dwell upon the earth ſhall worſhip him, i. e. the Beaſt, whoſe names are not written in the book of the life of the Lamb, ſlain from the foundation of the world.</hi> And that Chriſt warneth us of the perill thereof, as ſuch which threatens <hi>to deceive if it were poſſible the very Elect.</hi> The ſtrength of falſe prophecy lay not in the argument of the ſpeaker, but in the affection of the hearer. <hi>My people love
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171454:15"/>
to have it ſo. Jer.</hi> 5.32. The conjunction of a Judicial diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with a pleaſing error, &amp; an itching ear, preſents a ſufficient reaſon why men otherwiſe rational, are intoxicated with doctrines moſt irreligious &amp; irrational. Why the ſucceſs of falſe teachers (at times) hath been ſuch, as hath exceeded their own expectation Hence was the ground of that old ſaying of the <hi>Monk,</hi> inſulting over the peoples credulity, <hi>Si mundus vult decipi, decipiatur. If the world will be deceived, let it be deceived.</hi> When the <hi>Duke of Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony</hi> affected with <hi>Muncer's</hi> crying out under the ſeverity of his tortures, ſaid unto him, <hi>truely Muncer you indure at preſent, but think alſo upon the ruine of ſo many poor people, which at this day by occaſion of your ſeduction, are ſlain. He anſwered after a laughing manner, they would ſo have it.</hi> Whether it were more wickedly done in <hi>Muncer</hi> that thus mocked, or it more juſtly befell the miſerable people thus to be mocked, the reader may conſider. <hi>Paraeus</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whileſt he reports of a <hi>Papist glorying over his countrey-men, that if the Pope ſhould ſo Command the Germans under pretence of the redemption of their ſouls, they would eat hay &amp; graſs like Cattel.</hi> wo, be to Ahab when both God, the lying prophets, and himſelf, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirer ſpectively the ſame deception, unto his deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Though the being of hereſies be a great evill, yet <hi>hereſies must be:</hi> as ſerving the counſell of God unto divine uſes. In reſpect of the world: in reſpect of the profeſſors of the truth, both hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, &amp; ſincere: In reſpect of the world. <hi>Ma.</hi> 18.7. <hi>woe be to the world becauſe of offences.</hi> Open enemies of the trueth rejoyce in them, harden their hearts in impenitence by them: whereby theſe veſſels of wrath, fill up their meaſure, and fit themſelves for their juſt, &amp; greater condemnation.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>hypocriticall profeſſors, God hereby diſcovers them. They went out, that they might be made manifeſt, that they were not all of us.</hi> 1. <hi>John.</hi> 2.19. God in his own ſeaſon, many times detects unſound profeſſors, &amp; Church members, in this life: to ſhew that whatever name they had in the Churches which they lived in, yet they were never unſeen to his alſeeing eye. 2. <hi>To make others afraid</hi> how <hi>they approach to his holy things in hypocriſy. Acts.</hi> 5.14. 3. <hi>To prevent others being deceived by them.</hi> When the ſtate of the repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick is quiet, all the members ſeem to be wel-affected, &amp; like minded to the ſtate: but as ſoon as <hi>Abſaloms trumpet</hi> ſounds, there quickly followeth a viſible ſeparation in <hi>Jſrael.</hi> Now <hi>David</hi> knoweth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171454:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
whoſe hearts are indeed with him, whoſe not. During the churches peace, all the members ſeem orthodox, but if a ſtrangers voice be heard, then the lovers of ſound doctrine &amp; itching ears, fall into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: &amp; follow not the ſame Teacher.</p>
               <p>As concerning <hi>ſincere profeſſors</hi> of the trueth: Teachers of falſe doctrine are unto them, as ſo many <hi>tempters</hi> or tryars. <hi>For the Lord your God proveth you, to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your heart, &amp; with all your ſoul. Deut.</hi> 13.3. Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an high nature, trying to the utmoſt, <hi>if it were poſſible</hi> as we ſaid before, <hi>to deceive the very Elect.</hi> Tryalls greater then thoſe of perſecution, exile, ſpoyling of goods &amp;c: Witneſs the ſad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy of too many, in this preſent aſſault of hetrodoxie, who quitted themſelves with reputation before men in the fore-named ſufferings. The ſame temptation managed under the notion of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and as the <hi>word of God</hi> prevailed: which propoſed by King <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> with <hi>the proffer of half his houſe</hi> ſuper-added, was rejected: 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.19, 8. Yet the demonſtration of their love to the Trueth is ſweeter then the probation therof is bitter.</p>
               <p>Furthermore falſe Prophets, do not only prove our ſincerity between God and our ſelves: but alſo;<note place="margin">1 Cor: 11.18.</note> 
                  <hi>occaſionally make it known unto others. For there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you.</hi> The manifeſtation of their zeal for the Trueth, was evangellically provoked by the <hi>antiperiſtaſis,</hi> or oppoſition of error. Error &amp; hereſie by accident conduce much, unto the furtherance of the trueth. <hi>Oppoſition occaſions light. Light proceeds unto confeſſion of the trueth. Confeſſion is a divine meanes of conqueſt.</hi> Oppoſition begets diſputation, that removes objections, and clears the trueth. Every article of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on triumphs upon a juſt inquiſition. Nothing prejudiceth verity more then the hiding, and ſmothering of it, by falſehood &amp; ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. The ſight of the trueth is the confuſion of the adverſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trueth cleared after us queſtioning becometh out of question.</hi> Nothing more approved, then that which is approved upon tryal. The invading of that great and myſterious trueth, by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>titrinitarians:</hi> ended in the eſtabliſhment of the doctrine of the Trinity.</p>
               <p>The faith concerning the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> was advantaged by its conflict with <hi>Arrianiſm.</hi> The doctrine of free grace, hath been triumphantly confirmed, by its conteſts with <hi>Arminianiſm.</hi> The point of <hi>Church-governmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> much more underſtood by reaſon of its
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171454:16"/>
man fold controverſies, with <hi>Antagonists.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The light thus vindicated, and illuſtrated by polemical la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, cannot be hid: but by the open profeſſion of the aſſertors ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neth forth unto the world. Witneſs the <hi>Apoſtle's Creed,</hi> (ſo called) with other eccleſiaſtical Creeds, whether proper, <hi>viz:</hi> ſuch as were ſet forth by ſingle perſons: or particular, <hi>viz:</hi> ſuch as were ſet forth by this or that Church: or general, <hi>viz:</hi> ſuch as were publiſhed by general Councils: namely the <hi>Nicene, Epheſine, and Chalcedon,</hi> penned partly for the better expoſition of the Apoſtle's, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that men might the better know how to avoid the hereſies of thoſe dayes. Witneſs the acts of orthodox Councels, down all along ſince theſe ancient times. Witneſs the <hi>Harmony of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions</hi> of the reformed churches, throughout the chief proteſtant ſtates: in the <hi>Century</hi> laſt foregoing (concerning which Century, as it cannot be denyed, that no one for many hundred yeares together ſo abounded with errors: ſo muſt it alſo be acknowledged, that no one, throughout ſo long a tract of time, abounded more with confeſſions of the trueth), and all thoſe worthy labours, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a ſpirit as zealous for,<note place="margin">Preface to the Harm.</note> as the enemy was malignant againſt the faith. Let them therefore (ſaith the godly prefacer) leave off, in mocking to terme us <hi>confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts,</hi> unleſs perhaps they look for this anſwer at our hands, that it is a farr more excellent thing to bear the name of <hi>confeſſing the Faith,</hi> then of <hi>denying the Trueth.</hi> Very notable, &amp; memorable is Chriſts improvement of the various and erroneous conceptions of man concerning him, unto a diſtinct and famous confeſſion of him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.13.-16. As alſo of that opprobrious apoſtacy of many of his diſciples, unto a moſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent profeſſion of him. <hi>John.</hi> 6.66,-69. Thus through the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious adminiſtrations of God, even apoſtacy it ſelfe from the trueth, occaſions a victorious teſtimony unto the trueth. Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous both in reſpect of the <hi>Confeſſors, &amp; Confeſſions:</hi> and they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>by the blood of the Lamb, and the word of their Teſtimony Rev.</hi> 12.11. The <hi>Confeſſor</hi> dyeth, the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> liveth The <hi>Conflict</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſors</hi> ceaſeth, but the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Confeſſors</hi> yet ſpeaketh, and <hi>conquering goeth on to conquer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſeeing the darkneſs which was upon the face of the earth, at the paſſion of Chriſt, feared a diſſolution of the univerſe: yet; Faith ſeeth that it is but an <hi>Eclipſe.</hi> The <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs will ſhortly ſhine again.</hi> Whileſt you look upon the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171454:16"/>
efficacy of error, with the eye of Reaſon, its motion ſeemes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed according to Satan's will: but whileſt you look upon it in the Scripture, you ſhall find its motions ordered exactly by, and ſubſervient unto Gods will. If you look upon the <hi>hour &amp; power of darkneſs</hi> as a man, it repreſents it ſelf as the apparition of <hi>Satan looſe:</hi> but if you look upon it as a believer, you ſhall ſee Satan in a chaine. The firſt aſpect, preſents all formidable, as the product of Satans will: which conteining the extirpation of all good, with the introduction of all iniquity, confuſion, &amp; miſery. (upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition it ſhould obtaine) what can be ſuperadded in the way of evill therunto? The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d repreſents every thing beautiful in its time it being an impoſſibillity, that he; whoſe <hi>wayes</hi> to his end are <hi>paſt finding out,</hi> ſhould do any thing, in relation either to way, or end: incongruous, or indecent unto him, who is abſolute perfection it ſelf</p>
               <p>Look upon the ſpirit of error in it ſelf, it is like the <hi>Lyon roaring upon Sampſon:</hi> look upon it in the Promiſe, 'tis as the <hi>Carkaſs of the Lyon:</hi> but behold there is a <hi>ſwarm of Bees, and honey in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſs of the Lyon.</hi> In its own nature, it is a <hi>flood of waters caſt out of the mouth of the Serpent:</hi> In the promiſe, it is as the <hi>waters of Noah,</hi> unto the freinds &amp; ſervants of the Trueth. <hi>When I thought to know this, it was too painfull for mee, untill I went into the ſanctuary of the Lord, then underſtood I their end. Pſal.</hi> 73.10, 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP: 3.</hi> Of the deſtructivenes of the Doctrine, and Practice of the Quakers; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto Religion, the Churches of Christ, and Christian States.</head>
               <p>DIſeaſes may well be concluded malignant, and mortal, at leaſt in their next tendency: when they ſeize vpon the vitalls and Spirits. The doctrine under examination, being cenſured according to this proportion, will ſoon be found guilty of the charge.</p>
               <p>The deſtructivenes of the doctrine of the Quakers unto Chriſtian States, appeareth; from
<list>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:171454:17"/>
                     <item>The nature of the Object they ſingle out, imediately to fight againſt, <hi>viz:</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>The Trinity.</item>
                           <item>Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>The Scripture as the Rule of life.</item>
                           <item>Order, both
<list>
                                 <item>Civil, eſpecially as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in al Chriſtian States with Power in matters of Religion.</item>
                                 <item>Eccleſiaſtical; as inſtituted in the Goſpel.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Spirit they are acted by.</item>
                     <item>The ſuitablenes of their doctrine unto diſcontented, ſeditous, factious, and tumultuous ſpirits, eſpecially if preſſed with poverty or a ſuffering condition.</item>
                     <item>The experience of the examples of their predeceſſors in Germany acted by the ſame principles.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Fundamentals in Religion are ſo denominated.</head>
                  <p>Principally, &amp; properly: ſo; Chriſt is a foundation. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16</p>
                  <p>Doctrinally: ſo; the Scripture is a foundation in that it holds forth the doctrine of life. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.10, 11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p>Practically: ſo; Order is according to ſome, not ineptly ſaid to be of the foundation: in that it is requiſite, in the way of means for the preſervation of what is fundamentall.</p>
                  <p>For the making good the firſt &amp; maine article of the charge; the clearenes of the trueth, of the heads inſtanced in, as the four parts thereof (their fundamentality, with the contrariety of the doctrine-impleaded thereunto being manifeſt) is neceſſary. In order whereunto (the Trinity and Scripture being ſome-what ſpoken to above, and that of the Perſon of Chriſt in this place not calling for it) it remaineth onely: to demonſtrate, 1 The nature and neceſſity of order: 2 That in their oppoſing the Magiſtrats, as now eſtabliſhed in Chriſtian eſtate: they oppoſe civill order.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the viſible-politicall-Churches Church-Officers Church-worſhip &amp; adminiſtrations, are Goſpel-inſtitutions, appointed by Chriſt, to continue to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Order is a divine diſpoſal, of ſuperior &amp; inferior relations, in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane or Chriſtian ſocieties, diſtributing to each one reſpectively, what is due thereunto.</hi> There was <hi>Order directive in Innocencie,</hi> order both directive <hi>and coactive, is neceſſary in mans fallen eſtate. Order is Gods way of lapſed mans wel-doing, &amp; wel-being.</hi> It is the forme of ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Formes are eſſential without which things cannot be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171454:17"/>By Order; plurality is formed into, and ſubſiſts in unity. Without it; plurality is but an heap. Neither nature, nor ſociety, whether humane or chriſtian, no not ſo much as a family can ſtand without order. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.22. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.19. If all were one member, <hi>i. e.</hi> if there were no order, where were the body? Order <hi>is a divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative of Trueth, Peace, and Communion.</hi> The good of Order is further intelligible by the evill of confuſion.<note place="margin">James 3.16</note> As <hi>confuſion is not farr from every evill work,</hi> ſo order hath a tendency to every good work, Order without action is negligence, action without order, is preſumption. Action without knowledg is reprehenſible, and order unprofitable: but <hi>Order, Action &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> perfect bodies Politick. The great good which is in order, is the cauſe why the wicked one ſo reſtleſly oppugneth it. The working of Satan againſt Order, is a policy, againſt a policy. The policy of hell, againſt the Policy of heaven. Whileſt we remember that God is the <hi>God of Order:</hi> it is not hard to diſcern the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligning therof, as proceeding from the Serpent: For <hi>God is not the author of confuſion, but of peace; as in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.33, 34. In Eccleſiaſticks it is a maxime indiſpenſable in <hi>Paul's</hi> motion, <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in Order.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 14.40. Doing nothing is more eligible, then doing without or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Many times there is not ſo much good in the matter done: as there is evill, in that it is diſorderly done. In Civills; in caſe of non-adminiſtration <hi>wickedneſs reignes. Judges</hi> 17.6. In caſe of mal-adminiſtration incorrigible in the Magiſtrate, the Pſalmiſt cryeth out, that <hi>the foundations of the earth are out of courſe. Pſal:</hi> 82.5. Such a foundation then is Order, as it <hi>being caſt down, what ſhall the Righteous do?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Their Oppoſition to Civil Order, is thus evinced.</head>
                  <p>That doctrine which denyeth obedience unto the order of Magiſtracy in its due ſubject, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. interpretatively, and in effect denyeth the order of Magiſtracy, <hi>i. e.</hi> Civil order.</p>
                  <p>But their doctrine denieth Obedience unto the order of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, in its due ſubject.</p>
                  <p>Therefore their doctrine denyeth the order of Magiſtracy <hi>i. e.</hi> Civil order.</p>
                  <p>That they deny obedience unto the order of Magiſtracy, in its due ſubject: witneſs both their <hi>ſcripts, &amp; behaviour,</hi> wherin they deny obedience unto all Chriſtian Magiſtrates, who are not of their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171454:18"/>
own mind. Their pernicious principles herein, (from the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which the good hand of God hath hitherto reſtrained them) are notoriouſly palpable in the practiſe of <hi>Storke &amp; Mancer,</hi> their Predeceſſors. About 1521. <hi>Nicholas Storke,</hi> a ring-leader a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a company of mutinous, and ſeditious perſons, pretended to immediate viſions: and thereupon, preached; that <hi>there ſhould come a new world, wherein ſhould dwell Righteouſneſs: therefore they ought to exterminate all the wicked, withall the Princes &amp; unbelieving Magiſtrates from the earth.</hi> They (faith the Author) called all thoſe unbelievers, which were not of their faith &amp; faction. In <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad, a Town in the Earledome of Manifield,</hi> one of the 4. Eſtates in upper <hi>Saxonie, Thomas Mancer</hi> enrolls the names of them, which were entered into league with him, and by ſolemn Oath promiſed aſſiſtance to diſpatch the wicked Prince, &amp; to ſubſtitute new ones.</p>
                  <p>They (ſaith the ſame Author) generally <hi>accounted all Superiours wicked.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The being of Magiſtracy is from God immediately: <hi>There is no Power but of God, the Powers that be, are or lained of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This or that Form of Civill government, is of God mediately, <hi>i. e.</hi> by the means of man. 1 Pet: 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man, for the Lords ſake. Wherefore yee must needs bee ſubject, not only for weath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake. Rom:</hi> 13.5.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Power of the Civil Magiſtrate in matters of Religion, See in the next chapter.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Viſible Politica-Charches, Church-Officers, and Church-Ordinances,</hi> are Goſpel-Inſtitutions, appointed by <hi>Christ,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end of the world, appeareth as followeth, briefly,</p>
                  <p>That Commandement which <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> gave to <hi>Timothy</hi> is to be <hi>kept untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus</hi> 1 Tim: 6.14.</p>
                  <p>But Viſible Political-Church eſtate is part of that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which <hi>Paul</hi> gave to <hi>Timothy</hi> 1 Tim: 3.15.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, Viſible political church-eſtate, is to continue <hi>untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> i. e. to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>The word <hi>[Commandment]</hi> relates generally to all conteined in this Epiſtle, &amp; preſcribed unto <hi>Timothy</hi> to be obſerved. Whence <hi>Beza</hi> readeth it, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eception rather then Precept. This is part of that <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> that great thing depoſited: which the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ſo frequently &amp; affectionately calleth up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n his dear <hi>Timothy</hi> to ſee unto. Yea; and ſometime forbeareth not, as with a ſevere
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171454:18"/>
and moſt vehement adjuration, to charge bin with the cuſtody of, 1 Tim: 5.13, 14, 20. <hi>I give thee charge in the ſight of God. O Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, keep that which is committed to thy charge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Either God ſince the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Ceremonial worſhip &amp; Polity of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> hath changed the Rule of Political Church-eſtate more then once: or he hath left his people without any Rule, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Political church-eſtate: or elſe, the Political church-eſtate inſtituted in the Goſpel, is to continue to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>But, ſince the inſtitution of the Ceremonial worſhip, &amp; Polity of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſrael</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> God hath changed the Rule of the Political eſtate of the Church but once: <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.26, 27. And it is not a trueth to ſay that he hath left his people without any Rule, as concerning the Political eſtate of the church: <hi>Heb:</hi> 3.5, 6. 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.14, 15. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.33.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, the Political Church-eſtate inſtituted in the Goſpel, is to continue unto the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paſtors &amp; Teachers</hi> are Church-Officers:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paſtors &amp; Teachers</hi> are to continue to the end of the world:</p>
                  <p>Therefore, Church-Officers are to continue unto the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11, 12. having inſtructed us, concerning the inſtitution &amp; uſe of <hi>Pastors &amp; Teachers,</hi> proceeds <hi>verſe</hi> 13. to inform us concerning their duration: where; unto that queſtion how long are <hi>Paſtors &amp; Teachers</hi> to continue? He hath prepared an anſwer long ſince, in thoſe words; <hi>till we all come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie of Faith, &amp; of the knowledge of the Sonn of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fullnes of Christ.</hi> Wee have in the text preſented before us, the duration of theſe Officers, deſcribed from two periodical, and indubitable notes. Firſt, the <hi>meeting</hi> of all the elect <hi>in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God.</hi> Secondly; the attaining of all believers unto a <hi>perfect man,</hi> or <hi>he full ſtature of Christ.</hi> By the firſt, underſtand the effectual calling, together with the perfect agreement of all the Elect in the faith. By the ſecond, the perfection of Chriſt myſtical. <hi>The head and members, Christ &amp; all believers, make one myſtical perſon,</hi> or <hi>one myſtical-bodie.</hi> The perfection whereof is he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e held forth, by a metaphor taken from the full ſtature of the body natural, after which there is no augmentation. Now the perfection or full ſtature of the body myſtical, after which it receiveth no augmentation,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171454:19"/>
imports, two things: Firſt, that no member ſhall then be wanting: ſecondly, that every member ſhall be perfect. From the premiſes, it being manifeſt, that theſe two periodical notes, ſhall not be untill the end of the world: therefore as manifeſt it is, that Paſtors and Teachers being to continue untill then, they are to continue unto the end of the world. Thoſe three verſes are as <hi>Aarons rod,</hi> an argument (were it alone) ſufficient quite to take away the murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the people. Yet, for the further ſatisfaction of the Reader, touching the Goſpel-miniſtry, two things may here not unſeaſonably be ſpoken to.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Concerning the nature of extraordinary Goſpel-miniſters.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Concerning immediate miſſion of perſons in theſe dayes.</p>
                  <p>Touching the firſt, <hi>Church-Officers</hi> are <hi>Extraordinary, i. e.</hi> but for a time: as, <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts Ordinary, i. e.</hi> ſuch whoſe function continueth, and is ſtanding at all times.</p>
                  <p>To the conſtitution of an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> four extraordinary gifts concurred. 1. <hi>A Call immediately by Chriſt. Matthias</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in the place of <hi>Judas,</hi> is elected by Lot, which was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vote. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.26. <hi>Paul</hi> hath a viſion of Chriſt, and heareth a voice from heaven. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8. 2. <hi>Plenitude and amplitude of the power of the Keyes, i. e.</hi> all Church-power in all Churches. <hi>John</hi> 21.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. 3. <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſiſtance</hi> in their adminiſtration, when called thereunto. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21. 4. <hi>Power to work Miracles,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.12.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Prophets</hi> were called immediately by the Spirit: their work was to <hi>interp et dark Scriptures,</hi> by a ſpecial gift, without ſtudy. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.32. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14.24. <hi>Prediction of things to come, Acts</hi> 11.27, 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.11. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts</hi> 2.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.36 <hi>Acts</hi> 21.9. <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> were extraordinary Miniſters called by the Apoſtles, as ordinary Miniſters are by the Church. Such were <hi>Timothy &amp; Titus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> Touching the querie, <hi>whether we have any Scripture warrant to expect perſons immediately ſent of God in theſe dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>We have no promiſe of any ſuch ministry in our times. The laſt dayes Acts</hi> 2.17. are by ſome ſenced, as relating to the laſt dayes of the Jewes immediately preceding the dreadfull &amp; famous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of that Nation. (According to them) called <hi>the great &amp; terrible day of the Lord.</hi> Thus <hi>James</hi> chapt. 5.3. ſpeaking of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171454:19"/>
the wealthy Jewes ſaith, that they have <hi>treaſured up their wealth as fire against the laſt dayes i. e.</hi> againſt thoſe times of deſtruction when their wealth ſhould but do them a miſchief, marking them out as prizes &amp; preyes for the enemy. But this interpretation is left to free diſquiſition.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtles ſeem not ſo to have expected any ſucceſſion of Apoſtles. Hence in their life time, they appointed <hi>Elders in every Church, Acts</hi> 14.23. And left behind them, a preſcribed form, as a directory of the Churches, concerning perſons to be called by man into the Miniſtry ſucceſſively, in the ages to come. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3 <hi>Titus</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>But though we have no promiſe of any ſuch miniſtry, yet in the Scripture we have frequent prediction &amp; caution of pretenders to <hi>immediate miſſion, of deceivers, falſe Apoſtles, falſe Prophets, falſe Teachers, Speakers of lyes in the name of the Lord:</hi> with <hi>Command</hi> and directions <hi>to try them,</hi> not by their own <hi>profeſſion,</hi> for that is no great thing, if <hi>the miniſters of Satan transform themſelves into the miniſters of Righteouſneſs.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.15. Nor ſo much by their <hi>Converſation,</hi> (for the trueth were not true if ſuch <hi>ravening Wolves did not come in ſheeps cloathing:</hi>) as by their <hi>doctrine,</hi> by which fruit they are in an eſpecial manner to be known. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2 Epiſt. 9, 10. Yea, and upon juſt tryal, ſo farr ought we to bee from being moved by them, in point of our faith, as confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pronounce them <hi>Anathama's.</hi> But though <hi>we or an Angel from heaven, preach any other Goſpel unto you, then that yee have received, let him be accurſed.</hi> As we ſaid before, ſo ſay I now again, <hi>if any man preach any other Gospel unto you, then that yee have received, let him be accurſed. Scepticks,</hi> &amp; all others, are he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce beſeeched to conſider what unmovednes and firmnes in fundamentalls Chriſt looks for, eſpecially from thoſe who would acquit themſelves as Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, in reference to ſuch deceivers.</p>
                  <p>Though we have no Scripture warrant to expect <hi>immediate miſſions,</hi> and have both frequent and ſolemn cautions, concerning the riſing of falſe pretenders therunto, yet it being alſo a trueth, that <hi>the holy One of Iſrael,</hi> hath not limited himſelf herein. When any ariſe with the gifts prementioned, and with the fruits both of doctrine &amp; life conformable to the Scripture, they are according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be received in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lords Supper</hi> is a Viſible-Political-Church-Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171454:20"/>
and is to continue unto the end of the world. <hi>For as after as yee eat this bread &amp; drinke this Cup, yee ſhew forth the Lords death untill he come.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26. In theſe words (ſaith <hi>Paraeus</hi>) is a tacite promiſe of the conſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Church unto the end of the world</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is a Viſible-Political-Church-Ordinance, and is to continue unto the end of the world. <hi>Teach and Baptiſe &amp;c: and loe I am with you alwayes to the end of the world. Mat:</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>Therfore viſible political-Church-ordinances, are to continue unto the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object: </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which in our tranſlation we read world; ſignifieth <hi>an Age,</hi> and according to this verſion, the text alledged, ſpeaks not of the continuance of Baptiſm unto the end of the world, but unto the finiſhing of the age, <hi>viz:</hi> of that miniſtration, or of the Apoſtles age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> The trueth of the premiſes already evicted, concludes this evaſion a falſity.</p>
                  <p>Hence it would follow, that the inſtant of <hi>John's</hi> death, the laſt ſurviver of the Apoſtles, &amp; the inſtant of the diſſolution of Church order, was the ſame. But that <hi>John</hi> did not thus underſtand <hi>Chriſt</hi> yea that Chriſt did not thus underſtand himſelf, witneſs beſides his ſilence of any ſuch notion in his Epiſtles to the other Churches, his writing expreſly to the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> that it was the precept of the Son of God concerning that Church, that they ſhould hold faſt the doctrine they had received, part whereof was chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch-eſtate <hi>not till John's death, but till Chriſt's Comming. Rev.</hi> 2.25. Namely to Judgment. If the words be underſtood by any, of his ſpeciall comming to them, by their perſonal deaths, the like alſo being to be underſtood concerning others, it effectually makes void this objection. Add hereunto that <hi>John</hi> by that formidable <hi>Anathema</hi> chap: 22.18, 19. ſecureth the obligatory obſervance of all the words of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> wherein is mention of Political church-eſtate, as alſo of the reſt of the ſacred <hi>Canon</hi> according to the judgment of the beſt orthodox interpreters, untill the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.7, 12, 20.</p>
                  <p>Neither did <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who lived in the time of the Apoſtles &amp; outlived <hi>Iohn,</hi> thus underſtand <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Witneſs thoſe Epiſtles, which are acknowledged by orthodox &amp; learned <hi>Criticks</hi> in <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity</hi> as genuine. wherein he atteſteth unto &amp; owneth many churches then in being by honouring of them with the expreſs titles
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171454:20"/>
of the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>This objection renders the motion of Chriſt retrograde, <hi>viz:</hi> firſt forwards, from the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ker d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpenſation of the law, unto a more cleare diſpenſation of the Goſpel: and then backwards again unto a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpenſation more dark, then that of the Law, wherein the people of God (may we credit the objecter) are for 1500 yeares <hi>left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Rule, without Order, without Seales, without any ſent by Office, to preach unto them,</hi> or <hi>any Church-Ordinance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Engliſh tranſlation is apt, and renders not onely a true ſenſe of the word, but alſo its proper ſenſe in this place, appeareth from a particular indiction of its various acceptions in the New Teſtament. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> according to its proper notation, ſignifieth ſuch a duration as is <hi>without an end for EVER.</hi> Hence in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto duration, it is uſed in diverſe notions. 1. <hi>For ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Iohn</hi> 12.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.51. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.16. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. The objecter reading the word in theſe and many other texts [the Age of a man] muſt therewithall a firm that the reſidence of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> the ſtate of grace, heaven and hell ſhall continue but the age of a man. 2. It is uſed alſo for a <hi>duration that is long viz:</hi> for all the tract of time, from its begin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing, untill ſuch a <hi>Term</hi> then ſpoken of. <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.32. 3. <hi>For the whole courſe of time. Mat.</hi> 13.39, 40, 49. 4. <hi>For the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, or frame of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which is the Subject of time: that duration being an inſepperable adjunct thereof. Thus it is rendered <hi>worlds. Heb.</hi> 1.2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.3. importing in born the viſible world. The world 2 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> 4 4. ſpeaking of this world as contrad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtinct from the world to come For there are two worlds: <hi>this world Iohn</hi> 12.31. <hi>and that world Luke</hi> 20.35. This <hi>preſent world.</hi> 2 Tim: 4.10 and <hi>the world to come</hi> Ephe: 1.21. This is the ſubject of the duration of time, that of the duration of Eviternity. Of the premiſed expoſitions the reader may ſoon perceive both from the ſubject matter ſpoken of and the collation of other Scriptures, that the third accepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only agreeth with the text preſented unto conſideration, and that this acception fully agree to therewith.</p>
                  <p>There is yet in the Goſpel according to ſome learned men, another acception of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, namely for the whole courſe of the time of the Goſpel-diſpenſation,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> after the abrogation of the Moſaical-diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, at the aſcention of Chriſt. This is called the <hi>laſt Age of the world,</hi> after which there is no other to be looked for by us here
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171454:21"/>
as after old age man is to expect no other age in this life but death, which putteth an end unto his time. And the Scripture (as they conceive) in this notion of age, relates to a very notable diſtribution (of famous account amongſt the jewes) of the time before and after the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> into two ages. The firſt is called the Age before the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the then preſent age, the age of the jewiſh ſtate. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the <hi>Age</hi> after the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the future age, the age of <hi>Chriſtianitie</hi> Not inconformably whereunto, <hi>Tobit</hi> ſpeaking of the ſecond Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple rebuilded under <hi>EzRA,</hi> ſaith that it ſhall be untill the end of that Age.<note place="margin">In natis ex Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bio E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang Demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra.t l. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Chapt.</hi> 14.5. And the <hi>Septuagint</hi> calleth <hi>Christ the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the age to come. Eſay.</hi> 9 6. And conformably hereunto, what wee read the <hi>ends of the world,</hi> they read the <hi>Conſummation of ages. Heb:</hi> 9.26. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.11. (The Greek bearing either verſion) conceiving that the <hi>Conſummation of ages,</hi> are therefore ſaid to be come upon them that live under the Goſpel, becauſe they who live under the Goſpel have out-lived the legal diſpenſation, the Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof was the conſummation of the age before the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and live under that diſpenſation, the ceſſation whereof ſhall be the <hi>Conſummation of the age</hi> after the <hi>Meſſiah, i. e.</hi> the Goſpel diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which ſhall be the ſhutting up of all ages, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly end with the end of the world. The ſum of this interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions commeth to this, <hi>I will be with you to the end of the age,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby the <hi>age of the Meſſiah,</hi> beginning at the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, and continuing unto the end of the world. It is the ſame in effect with the tranſlation, though differing in expreſſion.</p>
                  <p>Touching the <hi>Spirit</hi> they are acted from: their dictates are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by them, both as infallible and divine. Becauſe of the pretence of their <hi>infallibility,</hi> they muſt not be queſtioned. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the pretence of their <hi>divinity,</hi> they muſt be obeyed. What can be ſuperadded to the deſtructive tendency of ſatanicall motions armed with the perſwaſion of the indiſpenſable neceſſity of Gods own Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand. Their tumultuous motions are by grave Authors frequently ſtyled <hi>Furies,</hi> from the fiercenes of their Spirit in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of their Errors. Their agitation is like that of the ocean, when <hi>one would think the deep to be hoarie: raging waves of the ſea, foam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their owne ſhame. Jude v.</hi> 13. Erroneous zeal, heightened with intoxicating &amp; fanatick animoſities, is ſo much <hi>wilde-fire.</hi> But dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical zeal is ſo much <hi>hell-fire. A Spiritual frenzy. Being exceedingly mad againſt them. Acts.</hi> 26.11. Wicked perſecutors, who
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171454:21"/>
acknowledg not the faith are <hi>unreaſonable men: pray that wee may be delivered from unreaſonable &amp; wicked men.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.2. wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors who pretend to the faith, are <hi>mad men.</hi> The very light of nature teacheth all nations, that mad men acting according to their frantick paſſions, are to be reſtrained with chaines, when they can not be reſtrained otherwiſe. It goeth ill with the Saints, when <hi>they who kill them, think they do God ſervice, whileſt they rage accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their lusts.</hi> Woe to them <hi>who call upon the name of Chriſt,</hi> when he that <hi>verily thinks with himſelf, that he ought to do many things unto the utmoſt contrary to Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> not only <hi>breaths out ſlaughter,</hi> but is alſo Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſionated with <hi>letters from Damaſcus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their Doctrine <hi>carryeth meat</hi> for its followers <hi>in the mouth of it:</hi> ſo that its contagious influence in a ſhort time, upon the tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous nature of the diſcontented and irregenerate multitude, needs not ſo much to be diſcovered, as to be antidoted. That theſe perſons canonize themſelves as the <hi>Saints of the moſt High,</hi> is a <hi>ſtrong deluſion.</hi> And if they alſo by vertue of a <hi>forged Saintſhip,</hi> be heard intitling themſelves unto the Kingdom: and thereby; unto the dignities &amp; eſtates of all who are not of their mind, it will not be found more irrational, then <hi>Satanical:</hi> not more ſtrange, then pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. It may well be looked at as a Serpentine and inebriating ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageme, to make the power, honours, &amp; poſſeſſions of the godly, and others alſo who are not of their way: to become lawfull prize, and plunder to the ravening luſts of their <hi>proſelytes.</hi> For what then remaineth, but that a ſufficient number accepting of their doctrine agree together to poſſeſs themſelves of all that falleth within the compaſs of their rapine. 'Tis true, the Devills tempting of Chriſt with all the Kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them, <hi>All theſe things will I give thee:</hi> could take no effect with Him. But upon the tryall thereof with men of <hi>John of Leyden's</hi> ſpirit, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till tempter hath found better ſucceſs.</p>
                  <p>About <hi>February</hi> 1534 <hi>Rotman &amp; Cniperdolling</hi> ſend unto the neighbouring townes of <hi>Munſter,</hi> thereby giving notice to them of their ſect to leave all their goods, &amp; to repaire unto them, encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, that they ſhould not fail to receive more then they left behind them. Hereupon great multitudes both of men &amp; women hearkening unto thoſe magnificent promiſes, came in accordingly, and upon hopes of preferment, repair to <hi>Munſter,</hi> chiefly the poorer ſort, who knew not how to ſubſiſt. Some o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe 28
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171454:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Teachers</hi> of the world ſent out from <hi>Munſter</hi> (upon the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Father</hi> pretended to be given to <hi>John Twiſcoſcur</hi> a gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith) being demanded, why they expelled the honeſt people from the city of <hi>Munſter</hi> againſt their faith &amp; promiſe, &amp; detained their goods and by what text of Scripture, they could warrant that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes. They anſwered that the time was now come, wherein the word of Chriſt ſhould be fullfilled, <hi>that the meek ſhould poſſeſs the earth:</hi> and that GOD in this manner <hi>gave the goods of the Egyptians, to the Iſraelits.</hi> About the latter end of June, <hi>Twiſcoſcur</hi> calleth the multitude together into the market place, telleth them that he had a command from the <hi>heavenly father, that John of Leyden ſhould have the Command of the whole earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Oſiand. cent. 16. lib. 2. cap 33. Guide breſſe Cap: 4.</note> that he ſhould go forth with a mighty army, kill all the Princes promiſcuouſly, ſparing only the multitude, <hi>viz:</hi> thoſe <hi>who loved Righteouſneſs.</hi> That the time was now come, when the ungodly ſhould be oppreſſed, and the <hi>godly ſhould reign in this life.</hi> The King afterwards promiſeth to his 12 <hi>ſelect Captains,</hi> that they ſhould be Princes, aſſigning unto each of them their <hi>Province</hi> by name, as alſo <hi>Forts &amp; Lands</hi> which he would give them.</p>
                  <p>How potent a temptation, the opening of an opportunity to the irregenerate &amp; hungry multitude, of changing places with their Superiours, and poſſeſſing themſelves with their power, hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our &amp; eſtates, is: (When this temptation, is managed in a way of duty, and that duty alſo inſinuated from <hi>the higheſt nature, principle &amp; end, viz</hi>) Saintſhip of the higheſt form, inſpiration divine &amp; infallible, a ſuper-ſcriptural reformation guilded ouer with ſpecious pretences of the <hi>exaltation of Christ, and extirpation of Babylon:</hi> I ſay how threatning this temptation is, <hi>Engliſh men</hi> may not unprofitably collect, by recalling that perillous rebellion in the dayes of <hi>Richard the ſecond:</hi> raiſed from the doctrine of one man by a temptation of this nature, though then managed in a way of lawfulneſs only, not of duty. The ſumm whereof take thus. One <hi>John Woll</hi> a man of a factious ſpirit, perceiving the diſcontent of thoſe times: by two arguments, one taken from the <hi>equality of all men,</hi> as deſcended from Adam; the other from the <hi>injustice of the Laws</hi> upholding great inequality amongſt men: <hi>viz</hi> ſome Lords, and in large eſtates, whileſt others continued in a nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy condition, ſeduced the inferiour ſort, eſpecially ſuch as were pinched with penury, into a perſwaſion that it was lawfull for them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171454:22"/>
to help themſelves. Thereby procuring an inſurrection of Sixty thouſand, for the while carrying all before them, commiting diverſe murthers, many outrages, unto the entering &amp; awing of <hi>London,</hi> the terrour of the King, &amp; jeopardy of the whole Realme. <hi>Iohn Woll</hi> is peſtilent, but <hi>Iohn of Leyden</hi> is much more peſtilent. The ſtrength of this temptation lyeth not in the reaſon of it, but in it's complia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with corruption. Such is man's propenſneſs to the world, that where it offers it ſelf he is apt to haſten to it, though by a way which inferreth the perdition of the ſoul. No marveil if that Religion, which hath made the way to ſalvation, and to the worlds enjoyment, both the ſame and quick &amp; eaſy, be much fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: though not for Religion ſake, yet for the worlds ſake.</p>
                  <p>Howſoever <hi>Becold</hi> might ſmile in his ſleeve at the fallacy of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet therein he found ſweet, in that it promoted him from a <hi>Tayler of Leyden,</hi> to be <hi>King of Jeruſalem,</hi> yea; of the whole earth, and that all Princes muſt obey him, had their revelations prevailed.</p>
                  <p>To poſſeſs our hearts the more throughly with the peſtilence of the heterodoxie impleaded, conſider the diſmall effects which have followed upon the practices of ſuch, who have acted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to theſe principles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caspar Swenckfield</hi> an eloquent but unlearned man, ſpread his errours about 1520. The confeſſion of the Divines of <hi>Mansfield</hi> condemneth him, <hi>Anno</hi> 1555 and teſtifieth that he hath troubled the church thirty yeares.</p>
                  <p>About 1522 <hi>Nicolas Storke</hi> (of whom before,) rejects the Scriptures, as being a carnal &amp; literal Rule, holds forth revelations, thereupon the extirpation of the Magiſtrate, with a <hi>renovation</hi> of the world <hi>wherein Righteouſneſs ſhould dwell.</hi> Out of this ſchool came <hi>Muncer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>About 1524 aroſe <hi>Thomas Muncer,</hi> who in his letters ſtiled himſelf <hi>Thomas Muncer, the ſervant of God, with the ſword of Gideon against the ungodly.</hi> He cryeth down <hi>books, and the letter of the Scripture,</hi> ſaying the <hi>Spirit was Leader and Rule to believers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Amongſt other things he teacheth <hi>parity amongſt men, rejection of Dignities, Community of goods, that all the world ſhould abide in the liberty wherein it was at firſt created.</hi> Of his dangerous attempt in <hi>Alſtad</hi> to deſtroy the Princes, innovate the Government &amp; change the times, we heard alſo before. In <hi>Mulhuiſen</hi> an Imperial Citty in the <hi>Province of Turingia,</hi> he ſo wrought upon the people
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171454:23"/>
that they changed their old Magiſtrates, choſe new ones of <hi>Muncer's</hi> way, whence aroſe many troubles. Many people leaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his doctrine, defiſt from their ordinary Labour &amp; when they had need of any thing, they took from thoſe who had it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would or not. In <hi>Swaben &amp; Francony</hi> the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; labourers take up armes to the number of Forty thouſand, they drove away the Nobles, impriſoned ſome (according to the <hi>French Hiſtoriographer</hi> they ſlew many of the Nobility) ſacked &amp; burnt their Caſtles &amp; fortreſſes, as the fetters of their liberty. At laſt he &amp; <hi>Henry Pfeiffer</hi> pretending a viſion from heaven gather forces &amp; with a numerous companie take the field, fight with the princes are taken &amp; put to death 1525. In theſe tumults of <hi>Muncer</hi> were ſlaine firſt &amp; laſt fifty thouſand of the people: according to ſome one hundred thouſand.</p>
                  <p>About 1533 <hi>John Becold</hi> an <hi>Hollander of Leyden,</hi> by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation a <hi>Taylor:</hi> commeth to <hi>Munſter</hi> a Citty in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> with one <hi>Cniperdoling:</hi> where with their adherents &amp; followers, having gotten ſome advantage into their hand: Command is given, that ſuch who were <hi>not rebaptiſed, ſhould be put to death, as Pagans and wicked:</hi> but theſe troubles were iſſued by compoſition. In <hi>February</hi> 1534 contary to their Faith &amp; promiſe, they ſecretly fill the Citty with their own party. In the beginning they <hi>talked of nothing but spirit &amp; Holineſs,</hi> they ſaid it was <hi>not lawfull for a Chriſtian to be a Magiſtrate,</hi> and that it <hi>was not lawfull to bear armes.</hi> But after they had gotten power into their hands, then it was lawfull to ſeize the publick armes, to take the Town-houſe, to chooſe Magiſtrates to their mind, to reject thoſe who were ordained of God, to thruſt themſelves into their places. They that before cryed <hi>Repent, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> now change their voyce, and cryed <hi>Depart, Depart, if you will not die.</hi> Pillaging &amp; ſtripping honeſt people of all they had; forcing them out of houſe &amp; Citty with their wives and little ones, all that were not of their mind, without regard to age or ſex. Where (ſaith the Author) are thoſe fair ſpeeches now which were wont to be in their mouths. <hi>Do not reſiſt evil, He that will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy coat, give him thy cloak alſo.</hi> They command Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of all goods upon pain of death, they aboliſh <hi>Schooles and Courch-aſſemblies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Spanhem. hiſtoric. Nar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rat. Cap. 2.</note> yea ſo far (ſaith <hi>Spanh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mius</hi>) <q>proceeded the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this villanous fellow, meaning John of Leyden, that by the craft of a gold-ſmith of Warrendorp, ſuborned by him, who feigned a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171454:23"/>
revelation &amp; inſpiration, and the blockiſhneſs of the bewitched people: This ſcum of the earth was ſet upon a Kingly throne, &amp; excerciſed a ſtage-player-like Kingdom in an oppreſſed Citty, prepared himſelfe Princely furniture, and attendants, uſeth all manner of cruelty, with whoredoms, murders &amp; unheard-of tyrannie, diſtributed amongst his followers, Principalities &amp; Dukedoms at his pleaſure, by his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers: every where ſtirring up the country-people to mutinie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; yea, attempted ſuch miſchiefs, as will ſcarce find Credit with posterity: aſcribing to himſelf this frantick title: John King of new-Jeruſalem, King of righteouſneſs over the whole world.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon a Revelation of one of their Prophets, <hi>Henry Hilvers viz:</hi> that three rich Citties <hi>Amsterdam, Deventer, &amp; Weſel,</hi> were given to them: they attempt to take <hi>Amſterdam May</hi> 10 1535. and that ſo unexpectedly, wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly, and reſolutely, as that the Citty was not ſaved out of their hands without ſome danger and much bloodſhed.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Munster</hi> the King provideth a great Supper, the people ſit down to the number of four thouſand, the King, Queen &amp; Courtiers wait upon the table, Supper almoſt finiſhed, the King <hi>gave unleavened bread to all,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Take, eat, declare the death of the Lord.</hi> Then the Queen <hi>preſented the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Drink, declare the death of the Lord.</hi> Afterwards the King, Queen &amp; waiters ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; as they were at ſupper, the King ariſeth, ſaying, he had a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the father. Accuſeth a ſouldier: (which had been tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) that he was <hi>a Traitor,</hi> as <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>with his own hand haveing cut off his head, returneth to ſit down at the table,</hi> by way of merriment reciting what he had done. King <hi>Becold beheads Eliſe</hi> one of his Queens; and wives, in the market-place: becauſe ſhe had ſaid that ſhe did not believe it was pleaſing to God, that the people ſhould thus periſh through famine. At length <hi>Becola, Chipperdoling and Cretchting,</hi> being taken with the Citty, which they held till <hi>June</hi> 25. 1538. were tortured with burning pincers, then hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in iron cages, the King in the midſt, higher then the reſt by the height of a man, he endured the firſt three pinches in ſilence, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards cryed out for mercy, till he was diſpatched.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Matthiz a Baker of Harlem,</hi> a Prophet, after a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from heaven, Commands all books to be burnt, except the Bible. <hi>Herbert Truteling a ſmith</hi> hereupon called them <hi>dirty Prophets.</hi> Therefore <hi>Matthiz</hi> ſhot him dead. This <hi>Matthiz</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:171454:24"/>
by the impulſe of the Spirit without the Scripture, taketh a long ſpear, runneth up and down <hi>Munſter,</hi> crying out that he had received a Commandement from the <hi>Father</hi> to repulſe the enemy from the Cittie. He no ſooner approacheth the Camp, then a Souldier, one <hi>Miſnicus</hi> faceth him, and ſhoots him dead.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Sengal</hi> in <hi>Helvetia</hi> 1527 <hi>Thomas Schucker</hi> with a ſword beheads his own brother <hi>Leonard,</hi> in the preſence of his Father &amp; Mother, by the impulſion of the Spirit without Scripture.</p>
                  <p>Upon the place of execution he ſhewed no remorſe, but profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that <hi>it was the will of God revealed to him from heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Coppius a Flanders man, Quintinus a Taylor of Picardie, Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Perſevatus, &amp; Pocquius a Priest,</hi> who conitnued ſtill to ſay Maſs: in <hi>Holland, Brabant,</hi> and other parts of the Low-countrys and in <hi>France,</hi> ſeduced above four thouſand in <hi>Calvin's</hi> time.</p>
                  <p>All the murders, whoredomes, &amp; villainies (ſaith M. <hi>Rutherford</hi>) practiſed by <hi>Muncer, John Becold, David George, &amp; Swenckfield,</hi> they fathered on the Spirit, without the Scripture, or on ſuch an allegorick ſenſe as their <hi>unclean spirit</hi> expounded the word by: ſo as a man knows not when they ſin, when they ſerve God.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall take off my pen from tranſcribing any more of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, many wherof are at hand. What further troubles were cauſed by theſe factious ſpirits in <hi>Moravia, Bohemia, Poland, Hungarie, Auſtria, Sileſia, Weſtphalia, Freizland, Holland, and Brabant, in France.</hi> I leave the ſtudious Reader to inform himſelf from the hiſtories of thoſe times.</p>
                  <p>Did <hi>Luther</hi> in thoſe times write to the <hi>Senate of Mulhuſen,</hi> to beware of the <hi>wolfe Muncer:</hi> and have not we cauſe now to beware of the ſpirit of <hi>Swenckfield, Muncer, Becold &amp; Quintinus,</hi> more then reviving in this preſent doctrine of confuſion?</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Iliad ψ</note>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>Rem Regem, Regimen, Regionem, Relligionem</l>
                     <l>Tollere tentarunt.</l>
                     <l>Region, Eſtate, Rule Civil &amp; Divine,</l>
                     <l>Religion, ALL, they ſeek to undermine.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Amongſt theſe three wayes of teaching: Authority, Reaſon, &amp; Example: the laſt is peculiarly accommodated to the capacitie &amp; nature of man, as that which both inlightens &amp; affects.</p>
                  <p>Examples make difficult things plain, and doubtfull things certain.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171454:24"/>
Hence they are aptly called the <hi>Pledges of ſpeech,</hi> delivered for the aſſurance of the mind of the hearer, concerning the ſubject ſpoken of: upon the reception whereof, all experience atteſts unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive &amp; operative influence, concomitant in rational ſubjects.</p>
                  <p>It were a great violation of charitie to looke at all ſeduced as thus minded, we know the very method of the Maſters of Spirituall peſtilence, ſufficiently admoniſheth us that their novices are not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the heights of the <hi>myſtery of their iniquity.</hi> 'Tis probable that many of their conſiderable proficients are not alike inſighted into theſe ſecrets of darkneſs. Yea; that not a few of them, would readily &amp; really profeſs their deteſtation of the perpetration of the villanies forementioned. All which notwithſtanding, it were great defect of prudence, after ſo fair or rather formidable warnings paſt, and ſuch prodigious apparitions preſent, not ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly to put our ſelves into a regular and neceſſary poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Alas, men know not their deceitfull hearts. At the ſame time, we may both hear <hi>Hazael</hi> ſaying, <hi>But what is thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant a dog, that he ſhould do this great thing? and ſee the man of God weep, foreſeeing the evil that he would do unto the children of Iſrael.</hi> Be it ſo that many are led away in their ſimplicity, yet a diſcerning ſpirit may well doubt, that neither <hi>Achitophels head,</hi> nor <hi>heart,</hi> is wanting in the deſign. Beſides, why ſhould not men of the ſame Spirit (temptation &amp; opportunity concurring) be looked at as too like to walk in the ſame ſteps? From the ſame root, reaſon teacheth us (if not maturely prevented) to expect the ſame fruits: from the ſame principles, the ſame iſſues: from the ſame cauſe, the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. To give warning is the duty of the watchman; to take warning is the duty of the Citty. The experiences of generations foregoing, are the inſtructions of generations following. The hiſtory of the experiments of others is our advantage. The improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof in ſeaſon will be not only our duty, and wiſedom, but alſo a token of mercy. The woe's of Anceſtors, ought to be the warning of Succeſſors.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP: 4.</hi> Of the Remedy againſt Heretical doctrines, and in particular, againſt the doctrine of the Quakers.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding manifold evils prevailing, &amp; threatning yet the <hi>Prophet</hi> will not admit that <hi>there is no Balm in Gilead,</hi> that <hi>there is no Phyſician there.</hi> Though Chriſt hath not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171454:25"/>
ſeen good to exempt his with a preſervative from exerciſe by temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, yet hath he ſo provided, as to ſupply them with a defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative againſt the evill of temptation. There was not more ſicknes amongſt the people, then there was healing vertue in the Diſciples gift. <hi>Mat:</hi> 10.1. A venimous Serpent may be brought into <hi>Crete,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> but (may report be credited) no ſuch can live there. The wiles of the Devil are Serpentine and malignant, yet not to be compared to the wiſdom of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Serpent's head is poyſonous, but thanks be to God through Jeſus Chriſt, his malignity is both <hi>antidated &amp; antidoted. I will put enmity between thee &amp; the woman, between thy ſeed &amp; her ſeed. It ſhall bruiſe thy Head.</hi> Gen: 3.15. The Saviour of his people hath ſmitten Satan long agoe in his intellectuals. His plots are foreſeen, and the remedy hath prevented the diſeaſe. To Chriſt belongs the prerogative of being the only <hi>Politician.</hi> Now a compleat Polity exhibiteth meanes ſufficient, as to the ſufficiency of meanes, for the defence of the Law, and of all thoſe that are loyal ſubjects thereunto. Would the Patient but regularly attend the preſcript, there is no ſtratagem can infeſt the Churches, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence whereunto wee may not ſtill boldly ſay; <hi>yet there is hope in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this thing. Surely there is no inchantment againſt Jacob, neither is there any divination againſt Iſrael: According to this time, It ſhall be ſaid of Jacob, &amp; of Iſrael, what hath God wrought? Num.</hi> 23.33 <hi>mine eye affects my heart. Lam.</hi> 3.51. A due ſight of the Spirit of errour &amp; hereſie, is a great help to affect a Chriſtian Spirit therewith. Monſters in nature are eye ſores. The face of death, that <hi>King of Terrours,</hi> the living man by inſtinct turneth his face from. An unuſual ſhape, a Satanical phantaſm, a ghoſt, or appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion affrights the diſciples. The viſion of ſin unto a ſpiritual eye, is an object of much more abhorrence then the former. But the face of hereſie is of a more horrid aſpect, then all the forenamed, put together: as arguing ſome ſignal inlargement of the power of darkneſs, as being in a high degree diabolical, prodigious, &amp; portentous. Heretical doctrine is not only a ſin, but profeſſion of a doctrine which is both all ſin, &amp; a way of ſin. The ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of lies againſt the Lord and his trueth, deſtructive to the ſoules of men, and all this in the name of the Lord. <hi>Heretical doctrine conſiſts in the blaſpheming of the trueth as it is in Jeſus, as a ly, and publiſhing of a ly in the place thereof.</hi> The firſt born of Satan,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171454:25"/>
not a little aggravated in reſpect of its propagation by apoſtates, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe tongues which formerly bare teſtimony to the trueth, now bent againſt it, and for oppoſite errours. <hi>Thine own nation &amp; the chief Prieſts have delivered thee unto mee: what haſt thou done.</hi> If the people of God did well upon the hearing though of but ſingle blaſphemie, to manifeſt deep deteſtation thereof, by the rending of their cloathes; ſhould wee at the publiſhing of ſuch a compiled <hi>Syſteme &amp; frame of hereſie,</hi> which containeth many blaſphemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found inſenſible: would not their pious zeale riſe up in judgement againſt us? It is from the Spirit of trueth, to open our eyes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Spirit of errour.</p>
               <p>The remedie or Scriptural-preſcript to be applied in times of heretical peſtilence, conſiſts of ſome dueties common to all perſons, and orders: Some proper to families, Churches, &amp; the Chriſtian Magiſtrate. The Dutyes common to all are.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To ſanctify God</hi> in reſpect of his preſent providence, looke not upon theſe <hi>emiſſaries of Satan</hi> as caſuall or deſpicable, but as <hi>commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionated executioners</hi> of Gods coercive &amp; vindictive diſpleaſure, for our abuſe of the Goſpel without repentance: of which before: Chap. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To juſtify God in the humble confeſſion of our ſin,</hi> &amp; acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this his righteous &amp; tremendous diſpenſation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>A ſpeedie and effectuall endeavour to ſtabliſh our hearts in the trueth. That wee henceforth be no more children toſſed to &amp; fro: and carried about with every wind of doctrine. Ephe.</hi> 4.14. <hi>For when for the time yee ought to be teachers &amp;c: Heb.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Hold faſt that which is good.</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.21. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13.25. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 3.3, 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſtingwiſh</hi> between <hi>queſtions of docility</hi> or teachablenes tending to cofirme us in the truth: and <hi>queſtions of ſcepticiſme</hi> tending to hold the mind in an irreſolution concerning the trueth. Affectation of uncertaintie in matters of religion, is againſt religion. Certainty is of the nature of faith. Doubting &amp; Faith are oppoſite. To reduce trueth unto the hazzard, and promote errour unto the hope of a queſtion, is to render errour &amp; trueth of equall credit. An <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious leveliſme</hi> leading unto Atheiſme: and if the triall be before corrupt reaſon, as the judge: it is a notable ſtratageme to repreſent trueth for errour, &amp; errour for trueth. The ſerpents art in managing the firſt temptation was by way of queſtion: <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:171454:26"/>
                  <hi>Gen:</hi> 3.1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty between two Opinions</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Iſraels halting:</hi> Advantagious indeed unto <hi>Baal's</hi> followers, but an evill unſufferable unto the holy ſpirit of <hi>Elijah,</hi> zealous that the people of God ſhould walk upright. No marveil the ſtate was diſtracted whileſt religion was unſetled. So farr as the way whereby we ſhould ſerve God is a queſtion, it is out of queſtion, we cannot ſerve God. <hi>Scopticiſm</hi> in all points of faith is deſervedly abhorred,<note place="margin">See Kecker. Gymnaſ. Log. lib. 2. cap. 7.</note> but eſpecially in fundamentals. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous births</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plato) are not brought to light,</hi> neither are porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous diſputations, and monſtrous opinions to be ſuffered in the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Fidelity in walking according to the trueth. If any man will do his will, he ſhall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God or whether I ſpeak of my ſelf. John.</hi> 7.27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Duties incumbent upon the heads of families are Exemplarines. Inſtruction, &amp; Government. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Churches Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> All experience proveth, that the bitter root of hereſie, hath never prevailed, where Doctrine, Catechiſm, and Diſcipline have been upheld in their purity &amp; vigour. Concerning the power and duty of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate in matters of Religion, it is ſummarily ſpoken to in the Authors preface unto the ſufferings of Chriſt. But full information is at hand, in diverſe elaborate and ſolid treatiſes upon that ſubject lately publiſhed. It may therfore ſuffice at Preſent, to preſent the Reader with ſome texts to that purpoſe. <hi>And thou ſhalt speak unto the children of Iſrael, ſaying who ſoever curſeth his God, ſhall bear his ſin. And he that blaſphemeth the Name of the Lord, he ſhall ſurely be put to death, and all the Congregation ſhall certainly ſtone him: as well the ſtranger, as he that is born in the land, when he blaſphemeth the name of the Lord, ſhall be put to death.</hi> Lev: 24.15, 16: But other Scriptures omitted. I ſhall here tranſcribe only two more, both which are eminently pregnant with this trueth: wherein alſo are caſes put between the cauſe of God, and our neer relations, on purpoſe to provide againſt obſtructions in this great buſineſs of Religion.</p>
               <p>The firſt we have <hi>Deut:</hi> 13. <hi>per totum.</hi> Relating to all times ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding that conſtitution: <hi>If thy brother, the ſon of thy mother, or thy ſon, or thy daughter, or the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe of thy boſome, or thy freind which is as thine own ſoul, intice thee ſecretly, ſaying: Let us go and ſerve other gods: thou ſhalt not conſent unto him, nor hearken unto him, neither
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171454:26"/>
ſhall thine eye pitty him, neither ſhalt thou ſpare, neither ſhalt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale him: but thou ſhalt ſurely kill him, thine hand ſhall be first upon him to put him to death, &amp; afterward the hand of all the people. verſ.</hi> 6, 8. The ſecond wee have <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1, 3. <hi>Expreſſely relating unto the times of the Goſpel. In that day</hi> viz: after the Comming of the Meſſiah in the time of the Goſpel when the <hi>families of the tribes ſhall mourne Chapt.</hi> 12.11. The familie <hi>of the houſe of David apart, &amp; the familie of the houſe of Nathan apart &amp;c: There ſhall be a fountain opened i.e.</hi> the doctrine of Chriſt under Moſes diſpenſation is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>a fountain vailed</hi> 2 Cor: 3.13. &amp;c: Under the Goſpel-diſpenſation, unto <hi>a fountain opened.</hi> The vail of the Temple &amp; the ceremonial law being taken away. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs that when any ſhall yet Prophecie, then his father &amp; his mother that begat him, ſhall thruſt him through, when he propheſieth.</hi> Theſe words [thruſt him through] may be underſtood either of a Capital pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment Juridically diſpenſed, or of any other ſmart puniſhment piercing though not Capital.</p>
               <p>As God hath armed the Magiſtrate with Civil power for the defence of Religion, ſo hath he animated him unto the regular and ſeaſonable exerciſe thereof, by holding forth many excellent fruits, through the concurrence of divine benediction, concomitant and conſequent unto his fidelity in this duty.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The vindication of the name &amp; trueth of God from the diſhonour done thereunto by Hereſie, &amp; blaſpemie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Such Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themata Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calleth devotamenta</note> 
                  <hi>The Judicial conſuming of the Apoſtate-cittie by fire,</hi> was a repairing of the honour of God, who was before diſhonoured by the revolt of the inhabitants from him, by the meanes of Seducers. <hi>And thou ſhalt burn with fire the Cittie, and all the ſpoil therof every whit, for the Lord thy God: i. e. in Zeal of the honour of the Lord thy God.</hi> Deut: 13.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Hope of cruing the offenders,</hi> if they belong to God, as the healing of the delinquent is one end of the adminiſtration of Church cenſure: <hi>Of whom is Hymeneus &amp; Alexander, whom I have delivered unto Satan, that they may learn not to blaspheme.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.20. So is it alſo of Civil adminiſtration, <hi>and one ſhall ſay unto him, what are theſe wounds in thine hand? then he ſhall anſwer: thoſe with which I was wounded in the houſe of my friends. Zech:</hi> 13.6. The perſon queſtioned, who of a husband-man was become a falſe Prophet: &amp; now through Grace; having renounced that way of lying, and being returned to his honeſt old calling again, renders the ſharp
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171454:27"/>
ſtripes and chaſtiſements inflicted upon him, whether by his parents or freinds, authorized therunto, or by their procuring: as the means of his recovery. Here note alſo that this convert, howſoever whileſt acted by a Spirit of lying, he might look at the inſtruments of his chaſtiſements as perſecutors of him, &amp; injurious unto the liberty of his conſcience yet now being in his right mind, he both juſtifieth the act, &amp; ingenuouſly acknowledgeth them therin to have approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves reall freinds, &amp; cordial lovers of him in the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The putting away of evil from Iſrael. So ſhalt thou put away evil from the midst of thee.</hi> Deut. 13.5. Blaſphemous <hi>Benhadad's</hi> eſcape, is <hi>Ahabs</hi> guilt, &amp; that ſuch out of which he doth not eſcape. The not bearing teſtimonie againſt iniquities to be puniſhed by the Judge by meet execution of juſtice, renders <hi>Iſrael</hi> from time to time, both guilty &amp; ſcandalous in reſpect of ſuch ſinns. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of evil makes it the ſin of the delinquent, irregular permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof, makes it the ſin of the ſtate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The preventing of infection, and ſpreading contagion of an evil example. And Iſrael ſhall hear and fear, and do no more any ſuch wickedneſs, as this is among you.</hi> Deut: 13.11. Impunity of the ſinner encourageth others to do the like: but puniſhment ſpeedily and ſeaſonably inflicted, makes others more afraid of ſuch evills, then they were before. Sinn looſeth more by the execution of the Ordinance of Juſtice, then it gained by the ſcandal.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The preventing of the wrath of God, &amp; continuing the ſtate ſtill in the enjoyment of the protection &amp; benediction of the covenant. That the Lord may turn from the fiercenes of his anger, &amp; ſhew thee mercy, &amp; have compaſſion upon thee, and multiply thee, as he hath ſworne unto thy fathers.</hi> Deut; 13.17. The good of the regular execution of juſtice ſhews the great evil of irregular impunity. This abundant encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement from him that <hi>cannot ly,</hi> ſhould quicken the miniſter of juſtice to be as faithfull in the application of the remedy, as Satan is watchfull to cauſe the malady. Go in this thy might, and thou ſhalt ſave Iſrael from the forementioned evill doers. <hi>Have not I ſent thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>The interpoſal of Authority in matters of Religion,</hi> is a prejudice to, and a <hi>violation of liberty of conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Church-Authority is Authority: were this objection good the Church might not Authoritatively deal with any of her members for holding forth, or teaching of falſe doctrine. Contrary to <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171454:27"/>
12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2, 20.</p>
               <p>Diſtinguiſh between
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conſcience, properly ſo called.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The errour of Conſcience.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Conſcience properly ſo called, denoteth ſuch a knowledg of the object, as is in conjunction with, and is agreeable unto the knowledg of another, concerning that object. It ſuppoſeth two diſtinct knowers of the ſame thing, <hi>viz:</hi> God &amp; the conſcience. <hi>Conſcience is Gods vice-gerent in the ſoul.</hi> God is the abſolute and primary judge, conſcience is a ſecondary &amp; ſubordinate judge.</p>
               <p>Conſcience is the judgement of a mans ſelf, anſwering unto the judgement of God concerning him. Conſcience as operating, ſuppoſeth a principle enlightened, and erreth not concerning the notional &amp; doctrinal part of the object. Conſcience can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ly, witneſs the conſcience of the damned, that tormenting and never dying worm, conſcience as conſcience is a meer creature of God; but the errour of conſcience is from the old man, and the Serpent.</p>
               <p>Diſtinguiſh between Liberty of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Errour.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> (as relating to the queſtion under diſpute) is <hi>a freedom from all impediment in reſpect of man, as to the following of the dictate of Conſcience, in acting according to Rule.</hi> But liberty of Errour, or liberty of the error of conſcience, is falſly called li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience: being indeed oppoſite thereunto. It is a liberty in reſpect of man, to anſwer the dictate of the error of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in walking contrary to Rule. <hi>It is a liberty to blaſpheme, a liberty to ſeduce</hi> others from the true God. <hi>A liberty to tell lies in the name of the Lord.</hi> It is indeed a liberty unto bondage: The exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe very bondage. Reſtraint from it is a reſtraint from bondage. <hi>They ſhall put you out of their Synagogues, yea the time cometh, that whoſoever killeth you will thinke that he doth God ſervice. John.</hi> 16.2. To thinke the murther of the Saints was ſervice unto God, was not from their Conſcience, but from the errour of their Conſcience, and the practice of it a fearefull liberty. <hi>I verily</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>thought with my ſelf, that I ought to doe many things, contrary to the name of Jeſus of Nazareth. Acts.</hi> 26.9. <hi>Who was before a blaſphemer, a perſecutor, &amp; injurious: But I obtained mercy, becauſe I did it igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly.</hi> 1 Tim: 1.13. This was not from <hi>Paul's</hi> conſcience, which <hi>is a principle of light created &amp; placed by God in the ſoul:</hi> but from the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171454:28"/>
errour of his Conſcience, and (himſelf being witneſs) from his ignorance, which is of ſin and Satan, but not of God.</p>
               <p>The object ſubjected to the Coercive power of the Magiſtrate, muſt be ſome Act of the outward man. Tis not <hi>matter of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but <hi>matter of fact,</hi> which Civil-power dealeth with. Hence; ſo far is it from being a truth, that the magiſtrate proceeding accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Rule, either puniſheth or troubleth any for their Conſcience as that it neither doth nor can concern him, to meddle with the errour of their Conſcience,<note place="margin">Lex non Ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicat du oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultis.</note> as ſuch, be it hereſye; or whatſoever. Whilſt a man keepeth his heterodoxy to himſelf, he is doubtleſſe out of the reach of the Magiſtrate in that reſpect.</p>
               <p>Conſcience, properly ſo called, error of Conſcience or hereſy, hereſy uttered &amp; retracted, hereſy uttered &amp; not retracted but quiet, (called hereſy alone) &amp; hereſy Turbulent are all diſtinct, &amp; of diſtinct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. <hi>Hereſy ſchiſme, and ſedition, differ.</hi> Though uſually it falls out otherwiſe, yet a man may be an heretick, who is neither dogmatiſt, ſchiſmatick, or ſeditious: neither teaching his errours as truthes, nor cauſing irregular ſeparation from Church-Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, nor ſowing ſeeds of diſcord, or mutiny in the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Quiet hereſy,</hi> or hereſy alone; underſtand hereſy although uttered and not retracted, yet without endeavour either directly or indirectly tending to induce others to receive their errours: As alſo; without diſturbance of publick order, either eccleſiaſtical or Civil.</p>
               <p>This; divers godly-learned do not only exempt from the number of Capitals, but alſo ſeeme Cautious, if not ſilent, concerning ſubjecting it to any Corporal puniſhment.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Hereſy Turbulent,</hi> underſtand hereſy both uncured and incorrigible; <hi>i. e.</hi> in Coniunction either with, <hi>Teaching lyes in the name of the Lord.</hi> Or with diſturbance of publick-order, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil. This is not only heretical, but alſo peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and here is a ſeaſon, wherein it is the duety of the Civil-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, to put forth his Coercive power, as the matter ſhall require in the defence of Religion, Order, Church &amp; common-wealth.</p>
               <p>So farr is our doctrine from aſſerting ſubiection of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to the Coercive power of the Magiſtrate: as that we look at it as irrational, to extend his power unto the error of Conſcience as ſuch. We ſubiect not the bare propoſal &amp; owning of hereſie if cured: as obnoxious unto Civil authority. We affirm not that it belongs to the Magiſtrate to inflict any puniſhment for quiet
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171454:28"/>
hereſie. We affirm not quiet hereſie to fall within the neceſſary obiect of Magiſtratical Cogniſance, but leave it unto free diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We know that it belongeth not unto the Magiſtrate to compel any man to be a believer, nor to puniſh any for not being a believer. But we believe it belongs to him (in caſe) to puniſh a Blaſphemer, or turbulent hereticks, who ſeeth not a wide diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between theſe?</p>
               <p>Wee through grace abhorre prejudicing the liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the leaſt meaſure, and account ſuch report of us to be a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And through the ſame grace; Wee both dread, and beare witneſs againſt, liberty of hereſy, liberty to Blaſpheme the Bleſſed Trinity, the Perſon and Office of Chriſt, the holy-Scripture, the tabernacle of God, and thoſe that dwell in heaven. Howſoever fallaciouſly transformed into, &amp; miſ-repreſented under the plauſible vizard of liberty of conſcience falſly ſo called. We ſay Religion is to be perſwaded with Scripture-reaſons, not Civil weapons: with Arguments, not with puniſhments. But Blaſphemies immediate and hereſies carried on with an high hand, and perſiſted in, are to be ſuppreſſed with weapons &amp; puniſhments; where reaſons, &amp; arguments cannot prevail.</p>
               <p>We diſtinguiſh between Hereſie
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Quiet and alone.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Turbulent</hi> i. e. <hi>Incorigible,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſoliciting the people to apoſtacy from the Faith of Chriſt to defection from the Churches, to Sedition in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, And that after due meanes of conviction, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative Prohibition.</p>
               <p>We ſubject not any to Civil or Corporal puniſhment for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, if <hi>quiet and alone.</hi> We do not inflict any Church-cenſure in caſe of hereſie, without doctrinal conviction on the Churches part and contumacy on the delinquents part, foregoing.</p>
               <p>In caſe of <hi>Hereſie incorrigible,</hi> in conjunction with endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſeduce others thereunto, and tending to the diſturbing of Publick-order, we accknowledg it to be the pious wiſdom of the Magiſtrate, to proceed gradually, and where gentler meanes may rationally be looked at as effectual, there to abſtain from the uſe of any ſeverer remedie.</p>
               <p>And according to this method, hath been the gradual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the Magiſtrate here, with thoſe (hitherto incorrigible) <hi>Quakers,</hi> who from England have unreaſonably and inſolently
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171454:29"/>
obtruded themſelves upon us. 1. Inſtructing them. 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining them, untill an opportunity of their returne. 3. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing a law to warne and prohibite both them, and all others of their ſect from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into this Iuriſdiction: otherwiſe to expect the houſe of Correction. And in caſe they returned yet again, then to looſe one of their eares &amp;c.</p>
               <p>At laſt, upon experience of their bold contempt of theſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior reſtraints, &amp; that after their being ſent away againe, &amp; again, they continue to returne, yet again and again: to the ſeducing of diverſe, the diſturbance, vexation, &amp; hazard of the whole Colonie: The Court finding the Law paſſed, to be an inſufficient fence againſt theſe perſons, proceeded to a Sentence of Baniſhment.</p>
               <p>Their reſtraint before the Law publiſhed, was but reſtraint in the Priſon, until an opportunity of ſhipping them away. They who after the Law was publiſhed, would that notwithſtanding break in upon us from England, or other forraign parts, by Rode-Iſland, after their correction received, and diſcharging their daes, might return again to the Iſland, if they pleaſed: The wolfe which ventures over the wide Sea, our of a ravening deſire to prey upon the ſheep, when landed, diſcovered &amp; taken, hath no cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, though for the ſecurity of the flock, he be penned up, with that door opening unto the fold faſt ſhut: but having another door purpoſely left open, whereby he may depart at his pleaſure, either returning from whence he came, or otherwiſe quitting the place.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Sentence of Baniſhment</hi> as Circumſtanced, by an Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and equal eye, may be looked upon as an Act which the court was forced unto <hi>Se defendend,</hi> in defence of Religion, themſelves, the Churche, and this poor State and People from Ruine: which the principles of confuſion, daylie and ſtudiouſly diſſeminated by them, threatned to bring all unto, if not ſeaſonably prevented. <hi>Exile from a wildernes,</hi> from a place of exile; though voluntarie, from a place; confinement whereunto would indeed juſtly be counted exile, is <hi>an eaſie exile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object: </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>If it be the trueth of God which is pleaded for, it is below the trueth to ſtand in need of the defence of man, God can defend the cauſe of Religion without his help.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Whether this obiection, ſavour more of Inchantment, then an argument, <hi>i. e.</hi> whether it be looked upon as a meer argument or doth not rather give cauſe, to call to mind the <hi>witchcraft pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171454:29"/>
ſometimes upon the Galatians,</hi> is with the Reader <hi>whoſe ſenſes are excerciſed in diſcerning good &amp; evill</hi> to conſider. That a malefactor (eſpecially ſuch who <hi>chooſeth ſin rather then ſuffering</hi>) pleadeth for impunity, why ſhould it ſeem ſtrange? But to attempt the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting of the application of the remedy of iniquity, as iniquity. Antichriſtianiſm, perſecution, is indeed a device: and that as emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reaſon, as full of tranſgreſſion, A piece of the ſophiſtry of the Prince of darkneſs, to charm that ſword into a perpetual ſcabbard by a ſallacie, the dexterous &amp; vigorous uſe wherof, puts away the evill committed from, and for the time to come, prevents the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of evill in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But Chriſtians, eſpecially Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>ſhould not be ignorant of his devices.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>The Jewes acted with a ſpirit of mockery, hardned their hearts deſperatly, by putting the tryal of Chriſt upon a falſe diſcovery, <hi>Let Chriſt the King of Iſrael deſcend now from the Croſs, that we may ſee and believe. Mark</hi> 15.32.</p>
               <p>The <hi>queſtion is not concerning God's Power, but concerning his Will.</hi> God can preſerve his Truth immediatly without any external meanes but his pleaſure is ordinarily to doe it mediately. Hence he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded the Arke according to divine Inſtitution, with a double fence, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil. God can alſo ſave man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from evils committed againſt the ſecond Table, but hee ordinarily effects it by the helpe of the magiſtrate. The injurie done unto the trueth, hurteth man whoſe welfare depends upon the imbracing of it. It hurts not God, nor the Trueth in it ſelf, but only in the eſtimation of man. As Satan is permitted to raiſe up men to be offendors, ſo Chriſt raiſeth up men to be defenders thereof: to manifeſt that through Grace, the Trueth hath even amongſt men as great lovers, as it hath haters.</p>
               <p>When there was no Chriſtian Magiſtrate, God watched over the cauſe of Religion in an extraordinary man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er. The continuance of the gift of miracles, together with the then recent &amp; freſh memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therof conducing not a little for that end. But extraordinarie gifts ceaſing, and the Chriſtian Magiſtrate ſucceeding, God now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects the Civil power, in an ordinary way of Providence to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient therunto. God can bring up his ſons &amp; daughters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any uſe of Civil power: but it hath pleaſed him to <hi>appoint Kings to be nurſing Fathers, and Queens to be nurſing Mothers unto them.</hi> They are but ill nurſes, who ſeing the danger of thoſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171454:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
committed to their truſt, ſo much as in them lyeth, ſave not their nurſe-lings from the poyſon of the deſtroyer. A late &amp; memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble teſtimony of Gods owning &amp; bleſſing Civil Authority in the defence of Religion, who ſo conſulteth Hiſtory, ſhall find in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny flouriſhing Citties, and Churches, with other places of name, in upper <hi>Germany, Helvetia, lower Germany,</hi> and elſe where: Saved from the peſtilence of the Heretical and blaſphemous ſectaryes of the laſt Centurie, then deſtroying at noone-day: with, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the interpoſal of Civil-Authority, and that not once, nor twice, but frequently by the very ſentence of Baniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lyſander's</hi> counſel of old was, when the lions ſkin will not hold out, to piece it with a fox-ſkinne. Why ſhould it ſeeme ſtrange, that men ſpeaking doctrines of devils, and lies in hypocriſie, having their <hi>Conſcience ſeared with an hot iron,</hi> and therefore <hi>past feelling</hi> of ſpiritual weapons, object (may that ſerve their turn) againſt obnoxiouſnes to Civill weapons, of which they remain only ſenſible, that ſo priviledged with impunity, they may proceed in their madneſs without all reſtraint. That ancient ſtratagem of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers (otherwiſe often fruſtrated in their attempts) to open their way unto their flock, by endeavouring the removal of the keepers is famouſly notable from <hi>Demoſtheneſ's recital of the folly of the ſheep ſometimes delivering up the doggs that kept them, at the motion of the wolves. Whereby; he ſtayed the Athenians, from delivering up their Orators unto Alexander upon his propoſal: out of whoſe hands, they had been inſtrumental to ſave the City.</hi> Should the People not of <hi>Athens,</hi> but of <hi>Sion,</hi> ſuffer themſelves to be abuſed by heretical deceivers &amp; deſtroyers into a perſuaſion, that whil'ſt it is Lawfull for them under a praetence to invade, it is unlawfull for Civil power to defend Religion: they would render themſelves more like thoſe ſheep in the Fable then men of underſtanding in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not to make regular &amp; ſeaſonable uſe of the meanes, inſtituted &amp; bleſſed unto ſuch an end, in time of danger, is to <hi>Tempt, not to Truſt God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That God makes uſe of Civil power, conſequently of man: is not from his need of him, but his favour to him. Not from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of power, but abundance of Goodneſs. Notwithſtanding God could ſave his people without the aſſiſtance of man, and both could and did ſave them without <hi>Meroz, yet curſe yee Meroz (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof, becauſe thy came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171454:30"/>
Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> Judg. 5.23. If <hi>Eſther</hi> ſeeth her opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and that ſhe is come to the Kingdom for ſuch a time, Good. <hi>But if ſhe altogether hold her peace, God can cauſe enlargement, and deliverance to ariſe to the Jewes from another place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Albeit; as the Heterodoxie of the Sectaries pre-mentioned in the laſt Centurie, was univerſal, corrupting the whole body of Religion: ſo alſo Quakeriſm (as to the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof) their geniune offſpring, be in like manner a total hereſie, yet both becauſe the former is legible in many Authors, and the latter obvious from the penns and tongues of the preſent Dogmatiſts, and becauſe the ſcope of this diſcourſe is chiefely practical, the Reader may ſoon perceive way (other errors omitted) the principal heads of their doctrine, are herein onely conſidered.</p>
               <p>It remaineth that all orders &amp; perſons amongſt us reſpectively, Sanctifie God according unto the preſcript of Scripture, and that at ſuch a time: in the regular excerciſe whereof, wee may ſecure our ſelves of a greater bleſſing then the adverſary threatens trouble. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto former trials of our love unto the trueth, by leaving of our countrey, kinred, and Fathers houſe, and by the ſufferings of this wilderneſs: God in his wiſdome, now addeth this of trying us by falſe doctrine.</hi> That this divine fatal ſeaſon, appointed for the <hi>revealing of the thoughts of many hearts,</hi> through the judicial diſcovery of not a few (who have had a <hi>name that they lived</hi>) by their defection to hereſie may amongſt the reſt of the Saints, be alſo (through Grace) New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands <hi>manifeſtation to be approved.</hi> That the evill example of the Apoſtacie, of formerly fellow-profeſſors, may (as ſometimes the like did with the Apoſtles. <hi>John</hi> 6.) bring forth ſo much the more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous &amp; luculent a confeſſion of the Trueth. As the enmity of oppoſers increaſeth, ſo the teſtimony of the witneſſes increaſeth. Though the Beaſt blaſphemeth, the witneſſes overcome. <hi>Ye are of God, little children, and have overcome him, becauſe greater is h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e that is in you, then he that is in the world.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.4. The Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Adam ends in the confeſſion of Adam. The apoſtacy of both reprobate, Angels &amp; men, ends in the confeſſion of the Elect.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtacy from the Covenant of workes, ends in the moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious confeſſion of the Covenant of Grace. The greateſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacie, in a farr greater confeſſion. The threatning example of the revolt of many diſciples, with that of <hi>Judas</hi> foreſeen ſuperadded notwithſtanding: Chriſt well knowing how to improve the apoſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171454:31"/>
of hypocrites, unto the furtherance of his intereſt; in the very height of the ſcandal, put forth that queſtion triumphantly, not ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merouſly: <hi>Then, ſaid Jeſus unto the Twelve, will yee alſo goe away?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Rule of doctrine, diſcipline, and order, is the <hi>Center of Chriſtianitie.</hi> Sincere and grave ſpirits are like grave bodies, they cannot reſt out of their Center. <hi>i e.</hi> the Rule. <hi>Religion admitts of no eccentrick motions.</hi> Doctrine and actions not according to Rule, when quickened with erroneous zeal, are but run<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing ſo much the faſter out of the way. This people bought the trueth with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities: Countrey, Relations, Eſtates, oportunities, as to the things of this life, were Realities; ſhould wee now ſell it <hi>for that which is not Bread,</hi> yea, for Fanatick, Frantick, worſe then ſick Imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? What advantage will it be to have departed from <hi>praelacie</hi> to <hi>ataxie?</hi> From the Tradition of man, unto deluſions not onely contrarie to Scripture, but alſo unworthie rational men? Many &amp; moment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are the peculiar conſiderations, whereby wee are engaged in our reſpective ſtations to own our profeſſion, &amp; ſtand in the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and effectual defence of the trueth, with perſeverance unto the end in both.</p>
               <p>It concerneth N.-E. alwayes to remember, that Originally they are <hi>a Plantation Religious,</hi> not a plantation of Trade. The profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the purity of doctrine, worſhip &amp; diſcipline, is written upon her forehead. A ſpot of this vaſt <hi>Jeſhimon,</hi> converted into <hi>Corn-fields Orchards, ſtreets inhabited,</hi> and a place of <hi>Merchandize,</hi> cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate New-England. All theſe notwithſtanding, if ſhee fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from her profeſſion, call her <hi>Ichabod, the Glory is departed.</hi> In ſuch caſe, what was ſaid of <hi>Samnium,</hi> ſometime a famous Citty in <hi>Italy,</hi> viz <hi>that they could not find Samnium in Samnium:</hi> will be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied concerning theſe Churches, <hi>viz:</hi> that <hi>N.-E. is not to be found in N.-E.</hi> God forbid, that after N.-E. hath now ſhined twenty years and more, like <hi>a light upon an Hill,</hi> it ſhould at laſt go out in the <hi>ſnuff of Morellianiſm,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The converting of theſe and the like meditations, into ſo many Nayles &amp; Goades is not the leaſt part of the ſcope of this poor Script: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work of that one Shepheard: in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effectual looking unto whom for wiſdom &amp; faithfulneſs in ſuch a ſeaſon: the welfare of his few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heep in this wilderneſs, doth in a great degree depend. That whereſoever the Trueth lyeth, in the points now controverted, between the godly-Orthodox of the Presbiterian, and Congregational way, which the day will declare: We may yet when we ſhall ly in duſt, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve this report to poſterity, that as we renounced the pollutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Epiſcopacie on the one hand. So we kept far from the Tents of Morellianiſm, Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm, and confuſion on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other hand. And alſo, that having given in our Teſtimonie, againſt the Heterodoxies. Hereſies, and Blaſphemies of this Generation. We both lived and dyed. in the FAITH and ORDER of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Err. <hi>page</hi> 33 l. 17. Read Paſtors &amp; Teachers are to continue &amp;c: Paſtors &amp; Teachers are Church-Offic: erg.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
